<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A helpe vnto deuotion containing certain moulds or forms of prayer, fitted to seuerall occasions; &amp; penned for the furtherance of those, who haue more desire then skil, to poure out their soules by petitions vnto God. By Sam. Hieron.</title>
            <author>Hieron, Samuel, 1576?-1617.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1608</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 187 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 151 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A72314</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13406.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S123450</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99898566</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99898566</idno>
            <idno type="VID">173418</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A72314)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 173418)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2042:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A helpe vnto deuotion containing certain moulds or forms of prayer, fitted to seuerall occasions; &amp; penned for the furtherance of those, who haue more desire then skil, to poure out their soules by petitions vnto God. By Sam. Hieron.</title>
                  <author>Hieron, Samuel, 1576?-1617.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[34], 259, [7] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by H[umphrey]. L[ownes]. for Samuel Macham, and are to be solde at his shop in Pauls Church-yard at the signe of the Bull-head,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1608.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library, Oxford, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Devotional literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Prayers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:173418:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:173418:1"/>
            <p>A Helpe vnto Deuotion: Containing Certain Moulds or Forms of prayer, fitted to ſeuerall occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; &amp; penned for the furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of thoſe, who haue more deſire then skil, to poure out their ſoules by peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions vnto God.</p>
            <p>By Sam. Hieron.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Phil. 4. verſe 6.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>In all things let your requeſts be ſhewed vnto God, in Prayer and Supplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, with giuing of thankes.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Imprinted at London by <hi>H. L.</hi> for <hi>Samuel Macham,</hi> and are to be ſolde at his ſhop in Pauls Church-yard at the ſigne of the Bull-head, 1608.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:173418:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:173418:2"/>
            <head>To the right Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>the Lady</hi> Mary Strode, of <hi>Newingham</hi> in <hi>Deuon.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>MAdam, if I ſhould vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake a diſcourſe of the worth and excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of Prayer, it vvould be much harder for mee to keepe meaſure, then to bee furniſhed vvith matter. How it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded by God, and commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the frequent practiſe of all the faithful, there is no man rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Scripture can bee igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant: and what ſvveetneſſe it brings to the Soule and Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, by hauing ſuch a continuall
<pb facs="tcp:173418:3"/>
entercourſe &amp; communion with the Lord, I hope your Ladyſhip can witneſſe from your owne ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience. This is all I will ſay on the behalfe of Prayer, that as it is one of Gods titles of Honour to be ſtiled, <hi>The hearer of Prayers</hi> (Pſal <hi>65.2.</hi>) ſo to call vpon the Name of the Lord is put for the whole duety and as it vvere the life and ſubſtance of a Chriſtian. (<hi>1.</hi> Cor. <hi>1.2. 2.</hi> Ti. <hi>2.19.</hi>). Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is that vvhich ſeaſoneth all other ſeruices which we offer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, it is an argument of a mans effectual profiting by other exerciſes of godlineſs, it is a thing vvhich the perſecuters of the Saints, vvhen they violently cauſe all publike acts of worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping
<pb facs="tcp:173418:3"/>
God to be intermitted, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not abbridge vntil life it ſelfe be extinguiſhed. Much talking there is of Prayer in the world: but if, ſetting aſide mens lip-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, enquiry be made into them, what apprehenſion they haue of their owne wants, what conceit of the Maieſtie and preſence of God, what knowledge and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of his promiſes, vvhat care (when they come to pray) to watch ouer their own ſtraggling thoughts, and to tye their hearts to that buſineſs of deuotion, vve ſhall find ſuch an vniuerſal ſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie of theſe things, that it may bee ſafely affirmed, that albeit there be many kneelers and ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, and repeaters of words, yet
<pb facs="tcp:173418:4"/>
there are fewe true petitioners vnto God. Now among thoſe fevve which make conſcience to performe this duty as they ought, I haue obſerued a great defect: namely, that for want of exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vvits, of knovvledge in the Scriptures, and eſpecially of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in the power of godlineſs, and of a liuely ſenſe and diſtinct conceiuing of their own perſonall neceſſities, they are not able to bee their ovvne meſſengers, nor to doe their owne errand, in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting the ſacrifice of Prayer before the Lord. They vvould pray vvith their families, but they know not hovv; they haue a vvillingneſs vpon other occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions to become ſuters vnto God
<pb facs="tcp:173418:4"/>
but they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not deuiſe which way to begin. To helpe theſe, I haue lately taken a little paynes: not vvith an intent to bind their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotions to my words, (for vvho am I, that I ſhould take vpon mee to limit the motions of another mans heart, to a forme of my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſing?) neither yet to cheriſh any in this their inſufficiency to deliuer their owne apprehenſions and particular caſes vnto God: but that by ſeeing the order and courſe of Prayer, and by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainting themſelues with words and formes of ſpeach agreeing to the nature of ſuch an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe, they may at laſt, like little children, vvho by cree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, &amp; by the leading of others,
<pb facs="tcp:173418:5"/>
learne to go, be able to performe this holy duety with co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tentment to themſelues, and with comfort alſo to others vppon occaſion. Hauing ended this little labour, I emboldened my ſelfe to offer it to your Ladyſhip: not ſo much for your owne neede (who I hope are able with <hi>Hannah, out of the abundance</hi> of inward feeling, to <hi>poure out your Soule be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lorde, 1. Sam. 1.15.16</hi>) but as a pledge of my loue, and as a witneſſe of my thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe vnto God for his graces in you. And ſo leauing this Manuel with you, as a memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall of that reſpect which your Ladyſhip may many wayes chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge from mee, I pray God in
<pb facs="tcp:173418:5"/>
Christ to keepe you by his mighty Power through fayth, vnto Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Modbury, <date>
                     <hi>the 10. of October. 1608.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your La. in all Chriſtian duty,</hi> Sam. Hieron.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:173418:6"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian <hi>Reader.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>I Am not ignorant (good Reader) that ſet formes of Prayer are very diſtaſtfull vnto many: They are adiud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to bee a kind of confining and limiting of Gods Spirit: And ſome which doe allow them a lawfull vſe in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, doe yet not ſo well approue them for priuate pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes. For mine owne part, as I fauour neither their fondneſſe who ſcarce account it praying,
<pb facs="tcp:173418:6"/>
vnleſſe it bee by a booke; nor their careleſneſs, who labor not to attaine to an ability of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending their perſonall occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions (euen in wordes of their owne conceiuing) vnto God: ſo I could neuer ſee good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, why platformes of directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for thoſe, who are yet but beginners in this ſpirituall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of Prayer ſhould bee thought any way inconuenient or needleſſe amongſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. There is a great deale more arte in the cariage of a ſute to be put vppe vnto God (eſpecially when a man is to be the mouth of others, as in a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, or in viſiting the ſicke, or the like occaſion) then euery one, though perhaps hee haue ſome good feeling and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in Religion, can at the
<pb facs="tcp:173418:7"/>
firſt attaine vnto. Neither is it (as is pretended) any ſtraitning or bounding of Gods Spirit; but a meanes rather of quickening and ſtirring vp the ſpirit of him that prayeth, when he ſhall ſee the neceſſitie of bemoning ſome corruptions, or of crauing ſome graces, or of giuing thanks for ſome bleſſings recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, which himſelfe did not ſo much as thinke vpon before. Beſides, that hee may accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as his ſpirituall fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſhall increaſe, enlarge any particular requeſt, if it bee not ſo full to his preſent caſe; or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert his owne more perſonall concernements, which he, who went about onely to giue him ſome generall directions, was not able to coniecture. And touching that which I do here
<pb facs="tcp:173418:7"/>
offer to the worlde, I profeſſe ſincerely, that in my firſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking it, I had no mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to take vpon mee to ſet downe lawes for other mens deuotions, or to preſcribe any man in his particular occaſions of going to the Lord, to ſpeake ſo or ſo and no otherwiſe, as though I would reduce all ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications to be put vppe into the high court of Heauen, vnto a proportio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ſcantling of my conceiuing: He ſhal wrong me very much, whoſoeuer ſhall ſo imagine. Only this was it I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended and thought: I ſaw the ignorance of that place, where I liued. I had often &amp; earneſtly commended Prayer. I had ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times, with the beſt reaſons I could perſwaded the vſe of it in priuate families. I perceiued
<pb facs="tcp:173418:8"/>
withall in ſome, a better incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to it, then power to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme it. Hereupon I thought with my ſelfe, that as familiar Catechiſmes, and plaine Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes haue their vſe being ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the publique miniſtry, to bring thoſe, which are yet but babes in Chriſt (1. Cor. 3.1.) vnto knowledge; ſo alſo ſome helpe in this kind might bee good, to beget feeling, and to be a guide to thoſe which haue as yet but ſtammering and liſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping tongues, vntill they ſhall be able, hauing tongues as fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſiluer (Pro. 10.20.): plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and diſtinctly to ſpeake the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>guage of <hi>Canaan</hi> (Iſa. 19.18.). For this cauſe I gaue my booke no greater title the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> A HELP to DEVOTION, becauſe I would not bee miſtaken,
<pb facs="tcp:173418:8"/>
or thought to intend any thing els, but onely to further their religious purpoſe, who would faine learn to pray orderly and effectually vnto God. And in this courſe, I am ſure, that I am not without Examples. Worthy Diuines haue in theſe latter times beſtowed their paines this way: M. <hi>Iohn Brad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> M. <hi>Edw. Deering,</hi> M. <hi>H. Smith,</hi> M. <hi>R. Rogers</hi> (pag. 421. of his 7. Treatiſes.) M. <hi>Brinſly</hi> (in the ſecond part of the True Watch) and others whome I need not name. I might men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion others of other coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treyes, as M. <hi>Caluin</hi> (in the end of his Cathechiſme,) &amp;c. But the warrant of the Scripture is aboue all. I will ſay nothing of thoſe formes which wee finde appointed for publique vſe in
<pb facs="tcp:173418:9"/>
the Temple: that which I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour to iuſtifie, is the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of formes for priuate helpe. I might tell thee of the words of Prayer, which the Prophet bade the people to take vnto them, and to ſay vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord (Hoſ. 14.3): of the forme which <hi>Habakkuk</hi> was wont to vſe for the ignorances of the people (Chap. 3.1.): of the many Pſalmes which are ſtiled, Pſalmes of inſtruction, not onely becauſe the matter was of vſe to inſtruct Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, but alſo becauſe the very mould it ſelfe might remaine as a helpe in Prayer for thoſe, who ſhould at any time fall into the like occaſion, which the endi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the particular Pſalmes was exerciſed with. Theſe &amp; other things might I inſiſt vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:
<pb facs="tcp:173418:9"/>
But I finde a title giuen to one Pſalme, which ſhall be to mee in ſtead of many proofes, Pſal. 102. It is this: A Prayer of the afflicted when he ſhall bee in diſtreſſe and powre foorth his meditation before the Lord. Which Pſalme, thogh ayming perhaps at ſome more ſpeciall afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in which the ſeruants of God then were, yet inaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as it is reported in the title to be for the general vſe of an afflicted perſon (as indeede it is excellent for ſuch an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion) it ſeemeth to mee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly to ſatisfie all thoſe who ſhall doubt of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniencie of ſuch ſet dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions</p>
            <p>Thus hauing acquainted thee with my whole intent, and laboured (leaſt thou
<pb facs="tcp:173418:10"/>
ſhouldeſt be foreſtalled by any miſ-opinion) to ſhew warrant for my doing, I commend my endeauours to thee, and thee to the Lord, praying him to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh thee with the ſpirit of ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication (Zech. 12.10.) that thou mayeſt bee ſo full of holy matter (Iob 32.18.) and ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding with gratious ſpeach (Col. 4.6.) that thine ability to vtter thine owne feeling vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, may bring much ſweetneſſe to thy Soule, and no leſſe comfort to others, if thou bee at any time occaſioned to ſpeake in the name of others vnto his Maieſtie: Adding this withall, that if thou ayme not at this grace, but content thy ſelfe ſtill to ſpeake no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wordes but ſuch as are put into thy mouth, thou
<pb facs="tcp:173418:10"/>
wrongeſt thy ſelfe greatly, and all thoſe who haue laboured to bring thee vnto more perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in the Lord, <hi>Sam. Hieron.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:173418:11"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:173418:11"/>
         </div>
         <div type="notice">
            <pb facs="tcp:173418:12"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:173418:12"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A ſhort Aduertiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> touching <hi>Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration before Praier.</hi> In which is ſhewed
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>1.</hi> The neceſſitie of it,</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>2.</hi> The manner of it.</item>
               </list>
            </head>
            <div type="part">
               <p>THe neceſſitie of Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration may appeare ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie waies.</p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>By our ſauiours platform,</hi> in which the Petitions are not ſet downe abruptlie; but a ſolemne preface is prefix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, like a faire porch to a
<pb facs="tcp:173418:13"/>
beautifull houſe: to teach vs to frame our affections and ſet them in due order, before we draw neere to ſpeak vnto the Lord.</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>By expreſſe commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi> Bee not raſh with thy mouth, nor let thine heart be haſtie to vtter a thing before God. Eccleſ. 5.1. It is a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous thing to babble out vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digeſted &amp; vnaduiſed words in his eares.</p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>By example.</hi> O GOD (ſayth <hi>Dauid</hi>) mine heart is prepared, ſo is my tongue &amp;c. Pſal. 108.1. It was the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betwixt him and hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites, that he waſhed his hands in innocencie, before
<pb facs="tcp:173418:13"/>
he would compaſſe the Altar Pſal. 26.6.</p>
               <p n="4">4 <hi>By due proportion from outward things.</hi> If a man goe before a Prince, or man of au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, he will thinke vpon his cariage, he will ſet his tale in order, and meditate what to ſay: how much more then ſhould we prepare when we come to ſpeake to God, who is higher then the Kinges of the Earth?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>2</hi> The manner of Preparation ſtands in
<list>
                     <item>Praying,</item>
                     <item>Meditating.</item>
                  </list>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>PRaying:</hi> Meruaile not that I make Praying a prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiue to praier. A little eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:173418:14"/>
prepareth a weake ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, and ſetteth an edge vppon the appetite to eate more; ſo in prayer: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Dauid</hi> before prayer, praied, Let my prayer be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected in thy ſight as incenſe &amp;c. Set a watch, O Lord, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my mouth, and keepe the doore of my lips, Pſ. 141.2.3. A lifting vp of the ſoule to heauen, with a deſire of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, is a good prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue.</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Meditating,</hi> vpon three things: 1 GODS maieſtie: 2 GODS promiſes: 3 Our owne vilenes. The reaſon is this: There are 3 thinges chiefelie requiſite in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb facs="tcp:173418:14"/>
which are helped by this threefold meditation: 1 Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie and lowlines of ſpirit, begotten by the due conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of Gods Maieſtie; 2 Confidence and aſſurance to be heard, bredde by the knowledge of Gods promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; 3 Feruencie of affection, ſpringing from the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of our owne vile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
               <p>That the maieſtie of God muſt bee thought vpon, is proued, Eccleſ 5.1. Hee that ſpeaks to God, is bidden to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, that God is in heauen.</p>
               <p>That the promiſes muſt be muzed vppon, appeares, 2. Sam. 7.27. Thou haſt reueiled
<pb facs="tcp:173418:15"/>
vnto thy ſeruant &amp;c. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath thy ſeruant beene bold to pray &amp;c. Geneſis, 32.11.12. I pray thee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer me, &amp;c. for thou ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edſt, I will ſurelie dooe thee good. What courage can we haue to goe to the throne of grace without the warrant of promiſe?</p>
               <p>That our owne vileneſſe muſt bee remembred, it is euident. Gen. 32.10. I am leſſe then the leaſt of thy mercies. Ezra, 9.6. O my God, I am aſhamed and confounded to lift vp mine eyes, &amp;c. for our iniquities are increaſed, &amp;c. Thus then prepare thy ſelf to pray: Exerciſe thy thoughts
<pb facs="tcp:173418:15"/>
before hand vpon theſe three things: 1 what a preſence full of maieſtie thou muſt come into: 2 what ſweete promiſes he hath made to encourage thee: 3 what neede thou haſt to fly to his mercie. This will furniſh thee with humilitie tempered with cheerefulnes, &amp; both whetted on &amp; quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened by the feeling of thy owne neceſſitie.</p>
               <p>To helpe thy meditations of Gods maieſty, remember Pſal. 104.1. O Lord my God, thou art exceeding great, thou art clothed with glorie and honor &amp;c. 1. Tim. 6.16. who only hath immortality, and dwelleth in a light that none can attaine to, &amp;c. and ſuch like places.</p>
               <p>To ſupply thee with words
<pb facs="tcp:173418:16"/>
of promiſe: conſider Pſa. 50.15. Call vpon me &amp;c. ſo wil I deliuer thee &amp;c. Iſ. 65.24. yea before they call I will anſwer, and whiles they ſpeake I will heare. Iohn, 14.13. Whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer you aske in my name, that will I do: and many ſuch teſtimonies.</p>
               <p>To bring thee to ſee thy own vileneſſe, ponder Iob, 5.14. Man drinks iniquitie like water. cha. 25.4. Hee cannot bee cleane that is borne of a woman. Pſalme, 51.5. I was borne in Iniquitie &amp;c. Romanes, 7.18. I knowe that in my fleſh dwelleth no good thing. Gather account of thy particular
<pb facs="tcp:173418:16"/>
ſinnes as Iob did, Chapter, 9.3. View thy ſelfe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the glaſs of the Law.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:173418:17"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:173418:17"/>
            <div n="1" type="prayer">
               <head>1. A Morning <hi>Prayer, for</hi> pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate Families.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oſt gratious GOD and louing FA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THER, in all humilitie of ſoule, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fained acknowledgement of our bounden duty, we preſent
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:173418:18"/>
our ſelues heere before thy throne of maieſtie, and glory, deſiring in ſome meaſure to ſhew our thankfulneſſe for the multitude of thy mercies hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped vpon vs thy moſt vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ſeruants. By thee at the firſt we were fearefully and wonderfully made, thou co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueredſt vs in our mothers wombes, thou gaueſt vs the ſhape of men &amp; women, when it was free for thee to haue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualled vs vs vnto thy baſeſt creatures: ſince, it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thée to preſerue vs, to watch ouer vs and to guard vs by thy prouidence, to open thy hand, and to repleniſh vs with good things, to giue vs foode
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:173418:18"/>
and rayment, health, libertie &amp; peace: O Lord thy compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons faile not, but they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued euerie morning: euen in this night paſt, we haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued an apparant euidence of thy loue: For whereas, for the ſinnes committed the day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, thou mighteſt euen in the deade of ſleepe haue taken our ſoules from vs, and ſo ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly haue brought vs to our account, it hath been thy plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure yet to ſpare vs; and not onlie ſo, but to refreſh vs with quiet reſt, and to bring vs in ſafetie to the beginning of this day. Grant (O Lord) wee pray thee, that the ordinarie vſe of theſe thy kindneſſes, may
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:173418:19"/>
not make vs the leſſe to eſteem them: but ſo affect our hearts with the apprehenſion of them, that we may learne to admire thy mercy, which dealeſt ſo gratiouſly with ſuch vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full perſons as wee haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes béene, and may euen bind our ſelues to ſtriue to ſhew all obedience &amp; duty to thee, which doſt ſo enlarge thy goodnes vnto vs. But chiefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie (O Lord) raiſe vp (we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee) our hearts and our affections from theſe outward fauours (the leaſt of which notwithſtanding is greater then the beſt of our deſeruings) and drawe vs to the ſerious conſideration of thoſe bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:173418:19"/>
which doe more direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie concerne a better life. Make vs thankefully mindfull of the grace of election, by which thou fréely choſeſt vs in Chriſt to be veſſels of mercie, before we were; of thy ſending thy ſonne out of thine owne bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, being in thine owne forme, to take on him the forme of a ſeruant, and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come obedient vnto the death euen y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death of the Croſſe for our ſakes; of thy calling vs out of the kingdome of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes by the power of the goſpel preached, of thy ſhining into our hearts by the enlighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of thy ſpirit; of quicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vs when we were dead
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:173418:20"/>
in treſpaſſes and ſinnes; of thy begetting vs againe vnto a liuelie hope; of the firſt fruites of the ſpirit, and of that earneſt of our inheritance which thou haſt giuen vs: of the dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie free vſe and libertie of thy worde, whereby that great myſterie of godlines yea euen thy whole counſell is cléerelie reuealed to vs. O Lord teach vs to conſider what miſerable creatures wee were in our ſelues, &amp; what a fearefull caſe we had yet beene in, if thou hadſt left vs to our ſelues: that ſo the veiw of theſe vnſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and vndeſerued fauours may euen rauiſh our ſpirits, and ſo poſſeſſe our hearts that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:173418:20"/>
we may conſtantly reſolue, henceforth to giue vppe our ſelues as a liuing ſacrifice, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie and acceptable vnto thee, and to deuote all our powers both of ſoule and body to the glorie and honor of thy name. And (Lord) enable vs here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto we pray thée; for we are not ſuffcient of our ſelues, to thinke anie thing, as of our ſelues, we are naturally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate to euerie good worke. Open therefore the eies of our mind, that we may ſee what is good, and what thou requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of vs; teach vs to make thy word our delight &amp; counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor; that by it we may be infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in thy paths: put thy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:173418:21"/>
within vs, and cauſe vs to walke in thy ſtatutes; let our eares continually hear a word behind vs, ſaying, <hi>This is the way;</hi> giue vs hearts of fleſh, yéelding, &amp; pliable affections; ſubdue the crookednes of our nature, and bring it vnder the obedience of Chriſt. And when thou haſt entred vs into a good courſe, vphold vs therein by thy alſufficient grace, ſtabliſh vs in euerie worde and good worke, fill vs with the fruites of righteouſneſſe, let vs not be idle nor vnfruitfull-in our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion: but graunt that wee may bee euen rich in good workes, and ſo may adorne the doctrine of thée our Sauiour
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:173418:21"/>
in all thinges, making the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries of thy truth aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, when they ſhall haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing concerning vs to ſpeake euill of. And ſhield vs (O Lord) we earneſtlie intreate thee, againſt the malice and rage and fury of the diuel: giue vs wiſedome to diſcerne his policies, and courage to reſiſt euen his moſt fiery aſſaults: make vs wiſe againſt the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiling entiſements of this ſinfull world: let vs not be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried awaie with the ſtreame of theſe corrupt times: harden our faces, againſt the repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches &amp; enmities of euill men: ſuffer vs not to bee wearyed nor to faint in our minds for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:173418:22"/>
tribulations, ſanctifie vnto vs euerie affliction, that it maie bee a meanes to purge out our corruptions. Draw our mindes from the loue of this preſent world, teach vs to vſe it as if wee vſed it not, graunt that wee may euer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that wee haue heere no continuing citty; that ſo we may ſéeke for that kingdome that cannot be ſhaken, but is eternall in the heauens: Cauſe vs to depend vpon thy proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and to caſt our care and burden vpon thee; aſſuring our ſelues that thou which haſt gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs Chriſt, canſt not but with him giue vs all thinges alſo. And (Lord) if at any
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:173418:22"/>
time we fall by occaſion into a fault (as who are we, that we ſhould preſume?) put vnder thy hand we beſéech thée, deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs out of the mire that we ſinke not, let not ſinne ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low vs vppe, let it not grow ſtrong vpon vs, leaſt wee pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh. Enable vs vnto diligence and faithfulnes in our ſeuerall callings, teach vs to lift vppe our heartes to thee for a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing vpon our indeuours, and to remember that we are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes in thy preſence; that ſo we may ſtudie to walke with thee and to approue our very thoughts vnto thee. Giue vs a ſober vſe of thy creatures, make vs readie to reach out
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:173418:23"/>
our hands vnto the wants of others; beget in vs a godlie iealouſie ouer our ſelues, that we may walke circumſpectly, taking heede to our ſelues, in our eatings, in our apparell, in our companie, in our recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, often conſidering our wayes, and labouring quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie after euerie error, to turne our féete into thy teſtimonies. And (Lord) cauſe vs to be ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtlie mindfull of the eſtate of thy whole Church: bleſſe all kingdomes and ſtates profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing thy truth, bee gratious eſpeciallie to this our king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, forgiue the crying ſins of the times, continue thy goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, diſappoint the hope and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:173418:23"/>
of all Papiſts, let them periſh as manie as haue euill will at Sion, diſcouer Antichriſt more and more, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large the territories of thy church, ſtabliſh thy kingdome of grace, haſten the kingdome of glorie. Heape thy bleſſings vppon our gratious King, make him a further inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of much good vnto thy choſen, bleſſe his Quéen, proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per the worke of thine owne handes begun in the young Prince, ſhew mercy to the reſt of the royall progenie. Be gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious to the Councell, to the Court, the Nobles, the Gentry of the Realme, graunt that they may all ayme at the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouring
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:173418:24"/>
of thee, by whom they haue receiued honor amongſt men; Bee with the Magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy &amp; Miniſtrie of the Realme, make thy word to grow by the labours of thoſe whome thou haſt appointed to the ſeruice of thy church: Containe the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects in their due obedience to authority, bring to nought all tumultuous &amp; rebellious prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes; comfort al thine afflicted ſeruants, refreſh them with a ſweete feeling of thy fauour. Giue vs compaſſionate harts, and a fellow feeling of others miſeries; prepare vs vnto the daie of triall, and keepe vs by thy mightie power, through faith, vnto ſaluation. Graunt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:173418:24"/>
vs theſe good thinges, for Chriſts ſake: in whoſe name, wee commend our ſelues and our ſutes vnto thee, ſaying as he hath taught vs,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Our Father &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="prayer">
               <head>2. An Euening Prayer <hi>for priuate Families.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lord our GOD, moſt mercifull and gratious in Ieſus chriſt, among other thy mercies, with which thou doeſt euen follow vs thy moſt vnthankfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, we acknowledge this to be none of the leaſt, that we haue this comfortable free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:173418:25"/>
of comming into thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, there to poure out our ſoules before thee, and to laie open our neceſſities vnto thee. We praie thee teach vs to va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue this priuiledge according to the true worth thereof; that wee may come together to the performance of this duty with glad hearts, and cheerefull ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, reioycing in it that wee haue opportunitie giuen vs, to teſtifie ſome part of that great dutie, which in manie reſpects wee owe vnto thy maieſtie. And now (Lorde) being come before thee, wee cannot but confeſſe the vile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our eſtate: wee were conceiued in ſinne, and in ſin
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:173418:25"/>
wee haue continued all our dayes, wee haue euen drunke iniquitie like water, wee haue drawne it after vs, and tyed it vnto vs as with cartropes, wickedneſſe hath beene ſwéet in our mouth, we haue fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it and would not forſake it: we haue euen made a mocke of ſinne, and it hath beene a paſtime to vs to doe wickedly. Thou haſt often called vs, but we haue ſtill refuſed: thou haſt againe and againe ſtretched out thine hand, but wee haue not regarded: thou haſt ſought to reclayme vs, but wee haue hardned our neckes as it were yron ſinewes, and haue hated to be reformed. Thou haſt wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:173418:26"/>
to haue mercie vppon vs, thy ſpirit hath ſtriuen with vs, thy verie bowels haue beene troubled for vs; and how gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſlie haſt thou called vpon vs by thy word? ſaying, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne yee ſonnes of <hi>Adam:</hi> why will ye die? Come vnto me and ye ſhall finde reſt for your ſoules:</hi> Yet we notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding haue deſpiſed thy pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, wee haue abuſed thy goodnes, we haue turned thy graces into wantonneſſe, and haue giuen thee cauſe to heape vppon vs all thoſe fearefull plagues, and puniſhmentes, which in the extreamitie of thy law are belonging to the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked. When we looke into our
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:173418:26"/>
hearts, we ſee nothing but a confuſed heape of groſſe cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, vanitie, ignorance, frowardnes, vnteachablenes, dulnes, vnwillingnes and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aptnes vnto good, proneneſſe &amp; readines to any manner of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, ſecure, irreligious, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane, vncleane enuious, coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous and gréedy thoughts, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe and diſordred affections, all theſe (as it were) march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together to rebell againſt thee, and leading vs captiue vnto ſinne. The verie wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of our fleſh is death, and the ſpirits of our minds are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed: when we look forth into our liues, wee behold ſinnes more in number then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> haires
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:173418:27"/>
of our head: when wee take view of our ſelues in the glaſſe of thy Law, we can ſee in our bodies and ſoules, in our out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and inward man, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but vglines and defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie. Yea the ſinnes of this one daie are ſufficient to bring downe vppon vs the eternall weight of thy diſpleaſur. How negligent haue we béen in our callings! how haue we yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to our own vnbridled luſts in the vſe of thy creatures! how haue we cheriſhed in our ſelues worldlie, carnall and voluptuous thoughts! howe many bleſſings haue we vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankefully enioyed, neuer thinking vpon thee which didſt
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:173418:27"/>
beſtow them! how haue wee miſſpent this pretious time which thou vouchſafeſt vs! how manie good opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties haue we let ſlip, by which wee might haue edified our ſelues, &amp; done good to others! howe negligentlie haue wee kept our heartes, by meanes whereof ſathan hath got great vantage againſt vs! how ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derlie haue wee bewailed the iniquities of the times! howe poorelie haue wee ſtriuen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our owne corruptions! O LORD, if thou ſhouldeſt ſtraightlie marke our iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, O Lord, how ſhall wee ſtand, where ſhall we appeare, what ſhal become of vs? what
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:173418:28"/>
anſwere ſhall wee bee able to make thée to one of a thouſand. And yet (moſt gratious God) which is worſt of all, cuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome in euill, hath bred ſuch a hardneſſe in vs, and hath brought ſuch a cruſt vpon our conſciences, that wee cannot be perſwaded that thy wrath is ſo terrible, or our ſinne ſo greeuous, or our eſtate ſo wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full as indeede it is. Hence it commeth that we do not ſtand in ſuch awe of thy maieſtie, as we ſhould, we doe not ſo trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at thy iuſtice, nor eſteeme thy promiſes and mercies as we ought to doe: wee beſeech thée therefore to take the ſtony hearts out of our bodies, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:173418:28"/>
to put newe ſpirites into our bowels, that wee maie with feeling and with a liuelie and ſenſible apprehenſion, confeſſe our ſelues to bee, as we are; poore, and wretched, and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and blind, &amp; naked, ſuch as in whom there is no good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, ſuch as to whom there is nothing due but ſhame and confuſion of face for euer. And héere (Lord) according to that meaſure of ſpirituall féeling which by thy grace wee haue attayned to, wée doe vtterlie renounce our ſelues, wee doe whollie diſclaime all hope of help by our ſelues, we account all that is in vs but as droſſe and dung, and do moſt earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:173418:29"/>
entreate thee to looke vpon vs in thy ſonne Ieſus Chriſt; accepting his death and his paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as a ſufficient, abſolute and compleate diſcharge for all our ſinnes whatſoeuer. O Lord, let the chaſtiſement of our peace be vpon him, and let vs be healed with his ſtripes: we haue no other name vnder heauen in which we can be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: and wee know that thou haſt ſealed him, and ſent him into the world, to ſaue thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from their ſinnes: wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thée therefore for his ſake to bee at peace with vs, put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way our tranſgreſſions like a cloud, and our ſins as a miſt, forgiue our iniquities, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:173418:29"/>
our offences nomore. And withall ſeale vppe to our ſoules and conſciences the fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of this thy loue by the gracious teſtimonie of thy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that wee may know that there is peace in heauen for vs, and that Chriſt is made of thee vnto vs Wiſedome, Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, Sanctification, and Redemption, and that nothing ſhall euer bee able to ſeparate vs from thy loue in him. We doe begge this at thy hands, ſo much the rather, becauſe wée ſee the vanitie of all things in this world; all things in it are ſubiect to vncertaintie: they are all lighter then vanitie it ſelfe; But thy loue in Chriſt
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:173418:30"/>
is firme and perpetuall. For, with thee there is no ſhadow of change, thy calling and gifts are without repentance; and therefore wee pray thee, ſettle vs in the aſſured perſwaſion of thy loue, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end that we may haue ſome comfortable vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, that whatſoeuer do be fall vs here, howſoeuer wée be tryed, yet after all, we ſhall lay downe our heads in thy peace, and be made partakers of thy glory. In the meane ſpace, ſo long as thou ſhalt bée pleaſed to reſpite the dayes of pilgrimage vpon this earth, we pray thee, doe not leaue vs to our ſelues, neither forſake vs; but giue vs, as pledges of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:173418:30"/>
thy loue, thoſe Spirituall bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly things, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with thou art wont to furniſh thy choſen; that ſo wee may make our conuerſation ſuch as becommeth the Goſpel, wée may neuer diſcredit our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, or be a ſcandall and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence vnto others, but rather by our holy cariage may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke and winne others vnto thee. Helpe vs to this ende, wée beſéech thee, againſt our manifold infirmities, againſt thoſe euils to which our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures doe moſt encline, enable vs to ſhake off that ſinne that hangeth ſo faſt on: ſtrengthen vs to euery good &amp; holy duety, make vs perfit in good works,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:173418:31"/>
ſanctifie vs throughout, and kéepe our whole ſpirits, ſoules and bodies blameleſſe vnto the comming of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Make vs thankefull (as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth vs) for thy many fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours, for that continuall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation which thou affordeſt vs, for the comforts of this day both to our ſoules and bodies, for thy enlarging our time and opportunitie to repent: grant, we pray thée, that our thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe may not ſtand only in outward ſhowes, but that wée may be thankefull in déed and in trueth, labouring to be duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful vnto thee, which art ſo mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull vnto vs.</p>
               <p>And inaſmuch as, O Lord,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:173418:31"/>
wée doe profeſſe to beléeue the Communion of Saints, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it becommeth vs to bée mindful of others in our Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers beſides our ſelues: we are ſuters to thee on the behalfe of all thy people, ſparſed ouer the face of the earth: thou (O Lord) art priuy to their ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall wants: thou art onely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to make a gracious ſupply: we beſéech thée for them as for our owne ſoules. More par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, wee powre out our ſoules before thee for thoſe Churches which amongſt vs thou haſt planted and vnited vnder one gouernement. Our ſinnes (O Lorde) chiefly our contempt of thy glorious Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:173418:32"/>
doe deſerue a curſe, euen that thou ſhouldſt remooue our candleſticke, and cleane put out the light of thy holy word, and withall make vs a by word to the world by ſome extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie iudgement; But, wée pray thee in Chriſt, vouchſafe to reuerſe thoſe plagues which wee haue deſerued, continue thoſe fauours which wee haue hitherto enioyed, continue and enlarge the fréedome of thy word, ſtabliſh the trueth of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion amongſt vs by a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall decrée, both for vs and for our poſteritie after vs. To this end bleſſe all good means; aboue others, our Soueraigne and King, enable him euery
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:173418:32"/>
day more and more to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of that great duety wherwith thou haſt entruſted him; lengthen his dayes, proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per his Raigne, defeate his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies: giue him and vs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in his Quéene, and ioy in his poſterity; Encreaſe wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in his Councell, fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes in his ſeruants, loyalty and true-heartedneſſe in his ſubiects. Stir vp Magiſtrates and men in Authoritie, to ſéeke the aduauncement of thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and the wealth of thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Make thy Miniſters able and willing to publiſh the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret of the Goſpell, water their endeuours with the deaw of heauen, that daily ſuch as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:173418:33"/>
vnto life eternall may be added to the Church. And ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thou art pleaſed to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe diuers of thy ſeruaunts with the croſſe, ſome with ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of body, ſome with per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexitie of ſpirit, ſome with loſſe of goods, ſome with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint of libertie, ſome in one kind, ſome in another, we pray thee to ſwéeten their afflictions and to ſeaſon their ſorrowes with the comfort of thy ſpirit; furniſh them with a meaſure of patience agréeing to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of their trials, and put an ende to their grieuaunces when thou ſhalt ſee it fit.</p>
               <p>And (O Lorde) make vs ready for affliction: teach vs
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:173418:33"/>
to remember, that wée muſt through many tribulations enter into thy bleſſed king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
               <p>In our health, make vs mindefull of ſickeneſſe, of death, and of our laſt account; that theſe things may not come vpon vs as a ſnare, but that wée may bée prepared al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes in ſome good meaſure, to ſubmit our ſelues vnto thy moſt wiſe and holy appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
               <p>And now, O Lord our God, wée pray thée, to beare with the weakeneſſe and coldneſſe of our Prayers. Take vs this night into thy bleſſed tuition:
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:173418:34"/>
we know that thou doeſt nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſlumber nor ſléepe, kéepe vs from euill, kéepe vs from the malice of Sathan, from ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie and careleſneſſe, from dulneſſe and drowſines of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that if it ſhall bee thy plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to let vs liue vntill the morning, we may become ſo much the fitter to ſerue thee in our ſeueral callings, ſo as may bee moſt for the glory of thy great Name, through Ieſus Chriſt: in whoſe Name wee commend our ſelues and our vnworthy Prayers vnto thee, ſaying as he hath directed vs in the Goſpel, <hi>Our Father, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="prayer">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:173418:34"/>
               <head>3. A Morning Prayer <hi>for a priuate Perſon.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Almightie Father, the Father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and in him my Father alſo, how vnworthy and wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched a Creature were I, if re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing ſo many bleſſings fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee I ſhould not ſtirre vp my ſelfe to returne ſome thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe vnto thee for the ſame! It is euen thou (O Lorde) which from my firſt being vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till now, haſt couered me vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thy wings, and vnder thy feathers I haue béene ſure. My body &amp; ſoule, my health,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:173418:35"/>
my ſtrength, my maintena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, whence haue I theſe things but from thee? The ſafety of this night, the quiet reſt, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with I haue béene refreſhed, to whom can I aſcribe it but onely vnto thee? That I haue liued hitherto, that I haue not béene ſwallowed vp with ſome ſuddaine iudgement, that Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>than had not had his will vpon me, that I know the way and the meanes vnto a better life, that I am deliuered from the power of darkneſſe and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated into the kingdome of thy deare Sonne, that I haue daily acceſſe into thy glorious preſence, whence are all theſe, but from the freedome of thy grace?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:173418:35"/>If thou hadſt giuen mée my deſert, I ſhould haue peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed long agoe: it is from thy mercy alone that I am not conſumed.</p>
               <p>O Lord make mee aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of mine vnthankeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, wound my hart with the conſideration of my owne dulneſſe, whom ſo many kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes haue not wrought vnto more obedience. And vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe, I pray thee, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the ſmalneſſe of my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing, yet to looke graciouſly vpon this my morning ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of prayſe, which I do here tender vnto thy Maieſty: let not, I beſéech thée, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcantnes
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:173418:36"/>
and barrennes of my ſeruice, make thee to turne away thine eyes, and to haue no regarde vnto mine offering; But as thou art wont to ſpare thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants euen as a man ſpareth his owne ſonne that ſerueth him, and in them to accept the will for the ful performance: ſo be pleaſed to looke vpon mée in Ieſus Chriſt, and for his ſake to remit my former vngrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, and to ſtrengthen me by thy grace for the time to come, in ſome good meaſure to reforme the ſame. And to the end (O God) that I may ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt the trueth of my deſire to be thankefull, I beſéech thee, to beget in me a holy care both
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:173418:36"/>
this day and for euer, to walke worthy of that calling where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto I am called, to ſtudy to pleaſe thee with reuerence and with feare; &amp; by a blameleſſe, pure and vnrebukeable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation, to ſhine as a light amongſt men. I cannot, I confeſſe, doe this of my ſelfe, I haue in mee the ſame corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of nature which the moſt wicked hath: I entreat thée therefore to worke in mee that which is pleaſant in thy ſight: Giue me a cleane heart and a right ſpirit: make mee to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand aright the way of thy precepts, direct me in the path of thy commandements, knit my ſoule vnto thee, and make
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:173418:37"/>
it to cleaue vnto thy teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies: ſtay mee, and ſtabliſh me, that my foot-ſteps may not ſlide. Crucifie my fleſh with the affections and luſtes: mortifie my members which are on earth: ſuppreſſe and ſubdue that law in my mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, which leades mee cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue vnto the law of ſinne: Graunt that I may ſenſibly féele the power of Chriſtes death killing corruption in mee, and the power of his reſurrection raiſing mee vppe vnto newneſſe of life; Make mee to reſolue, to renounce euen my ſwéeteſt and beſt-pleaſing ſinnes, and not to take libertie to my ſelfe to
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:173418:37"/>
continue in any knowne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſſe. Let it bée inough that I haue hitherto giuen the raynes vnto mine owne luſts: graunt that heereafter I may take no thought for the fleſh, to content it, but may ſtriue rather to curbe and to ſubdue it, and to bring it vnder the yoke of due obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. And (good Lorde) encreaſe my fayth, and better my féeling and apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thy loue, that I may with courage and chearefulneſſe runne the race which is ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me; Bleſſe mee alſo this day in the dutyes of my cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. Idleneſſe and godlineſſe cannot agrée: and it is thy
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:173418:38"/>
will, that in the ſweate of my face I ſhould eate my bread: Preſerue me from all fraudu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, guilefull, oppreſſing, grée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy courſes: draw my affections from the loue of the world: fixe my heart vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the things which are aboue: If things ſuccéede according to my minde, make mee thankefull to thée which haſt giuen the bleſſing: If any croſſe come, make mee patient and carefull to profit by euery chaſtizement. And becauſe the daily occaſions of danger to my ſoule are infinite, teach me to put on thy whole armor, and to kéepe my heart with all diligence, to furniſh my ſelfe with holy meditations, to
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:173418:38"/>
make a couenant with mine eyes, to kéepe my mouth with a bridle for the auoyding of all filthy communication, to vſe ſuch words as may miniſter grace vnto the hearers, to bée ſober in diet, wary in diſports, moderate in apparell, choiſe in my company, and euer to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuall feare which hath a promiſe of bleſſedneſſe. Finally (Lord) ſo guide mee through the courſe of this whole day, both in my priuate and more publique imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that if I liue by thy ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferance vntill night, I may haue much comfort in the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king notice of thy grace and goodneſſe towards me: and all
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:173418:39"/>
this for Chriſt Ieſus ſake thy onely Sonne, and my alone Sauiour. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="prayer">
               <head>4. An Euening <hi>Prayer for a priuate</hi> Perſon.</head>
               <p>MOſt mercifull God and gratious Father in Ieſus Chriſt, were it not that thou haſt made a gratious promiſe in thy word, that whatſoeuer is aſked of thee in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of thy Sonne, ſhall bée beſtowed, I ſhould not dare to preſſe into
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:173418:39"/>
thy preſence, being guilty to my ſelfe of ſo many ſinnes which I haue heaped vp in thy ſight, from the beginning of my dayes vntill this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. I am by nature (O Lorde) the child of wrath, a vaſſall of Sathan, no better then a very firebrand of hell. It is thy great mercy, that I eſcaped the fury of thy wrath, due vnto mée at the very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant of my birth, in reſpect of that maſſe of corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which I brought with mée from my my mothers wombe. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haue I, ſince I came to vnderſtanding, any whit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended or bettered my firſt eſtate: but I haue added
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:173418:40"/>
to it a numberleſſe number of tranſgreſſions, breaking eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of thy commandements by thought, word and déede, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in many things againſt knowledge, againſt conſcience and againſt that light which thou haſt giuen me; yea, cleane againſt many vowes and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of better obedience. I haue no colour of excuſe, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing haue I to plead in the defence of my many ſlips: If I diſpute with thée, I muſt néedes lay my hand vpon my mouth, and learne to abhorre my ſelfe in duſt and aſhes. And (Lord) giue me, I beſéech thee, a fleſhy and melting heart, that nothing may more affect
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:173418:40"/>
mée, or touch me more deepely then to ſée my owne vileneſſe, and how diſobedient and ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne I haue béene towardes thee, which haſt euen heaped vpon mee ſo many fauours. Make me aſhamed of my bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renneſſe and vnfruitfulneſſe in my profeſſion, who haue giuen thee iuſt cauſe to range mée among thoſe hypocrites which make a ſhew of godlineſſe, but yet deny the power thereof. Beget in me that godly ſorow which cauſeth true repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce neuer to be repented of; that I may bee grieued in my very ſoule for my ſins, not ſo much becauſe of the danger of hell that followeth, as becauſe I
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:173418:41"/>
haue offended thee, the loue of whoſe maieſtie ought to bee a ſufficient motiue to obedience. And for the furtherance of my humiliation &amp; ſorow, cauſe me, O Lord, to ſearch &amp; to try my wayes, to call my ſelfe to a ſtraite account, that I may ſée my ſins in particular, the vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of my heart, my extreame deadnes &amp; ſecuritie, my pride &amp; hautines of ſpirit, my back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſſe to all good ſeruices, my worldly-mindedneſſe, my ambitious riſing and crauing thoughts, my want of charity &amp; mercy to others, my miſcari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age in my place &amp; calling, my idle &amp; vnbeſéeming ſpeaches, my offenſiue &amp; ſcandalous be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour:
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:173418:41"/>
thus (O Lord) make me carefull to rip vp my heart and life, that ſo I may ſet my ſins in order before me, &amp; may thereby become the more hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble &amp; the more forward to caſt down my ſelfe before thee, &amp; to iudge my ſelfe, that I may not be iudged of thee. Yet withall (moſt gratious God) make me able in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> middeſt of all this, to reach out the hand of faith, &amp; to lay hold vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ieſus Chriſt, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou haſt ordained to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciliatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for my ſins. I know (O Lord) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vertue of his blood, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it can make my ſins, though they were as crimſm, yet to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as white as ſnowe. O then (I beſéech thee) couer my
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:173418:42"/>
filthy nakedneſſe with his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious righteouſneſſe; cloth me with the garments of his Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that ſo therby I may be holy and vnblameable &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fault in thy ſight. Speake peace vnto my Conſcience by thy holy Spirit. Say vnto my ſoule, <hi>I am thy Saluation.</hi> My fayth (O Lorde) is but weake and poore: ſtrengthen it, I beſéech thée, and bring it forward, by thy mighty wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, vnto more perfection. Thou haſt promiſed not to quench the ſmoking flaxe, nor to breake y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bruiſed réede: beare then, I pray thee, with my ſcantneſſe, and helpe my vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe, perfite the worke of thy
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:173418:42"/>
owne hands, performe it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the day of Ieſus Chriſt. My fayth is that I muſt liue by; it is my victorie: thou (O Lord) in mercy haſt begun it: cheriſh it (I beſéech thée) toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with all thoſe graces which accompany ſaluation, that they may bee in mee, as a well of water, ſpringing vppe into euerlaſting life. And graunt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I may not be preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mingly ſecure touching mine owne eſtate, but may euer and anone bee proouing and exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning my ſelfe, whether I am in the fayth or no; and that I may alſo ſtudy and ſtriue to giue euidence of my fayth, by ſhewing forth good works, and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:173418:43"/>
by bringing foorth good fruite, euen fruite worthy amende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of life. I am compaſſed about with many weakeneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and (as I haue found by the experience of this one day) Sathan is full of mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious cunning, to worke vpon all aduantages; O Lorde, ſtrengthen mee to reſiſt him, giue mee holy wiſedome to to diſcouer his ſleights, and grace to withſtand his moſt ſharpe aſſaults. Arme mee alſo againſt the reproches and obloquies of the worlde. I haue learned in thy word, that if I ſerue thee in ſinceritie, my name ſhall bée put out as euill amongſt men: giue mée both
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:173418:43"/>
care to cary my ſelfe out of the reach of iuſt exception, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution alſo to ſacrifice my credit &amp; eſtimation, yea, euen my life it ſelfe if néed be, to thy glory.</p>
               <p>Teach mee to learne of the author and finiſher of my fayth, to deſpiſe the ſhame, and to endure the ſpeaking againſt of ſinners, in reſpect of that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall waight of ioy and glorie which is ſet before me. And now (Lorde) with the bowing of my Soule, I bleſſe thy name for this daies preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. How many euils haue I eſcaped to which I was ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect by nature, and to which I had made my ſelfe ſubiect
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:173418:44"/>
through ſin? It is thou (Lord) onely which makeſt mee to dwell in ſafety. Stretch out the wings of thy grace &amp; prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ouer me this night: though ſléepe ſeize vpon the eyes of my body, yet let not ſecuritie oppreſſe my ſoule: kéepe mée from idle fancies &amp; from vaine dreames: giue me a ſober and ſanctified vſe of al outward re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>freſhings, that I may alwayes in all things ayme at this one thing, namely, how I may be the better fitted to ſerue thee faythfully in my place and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; and that for Chriſt Ieſus his ſake, thy onely Sonne, and through thy mercy, my lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Sauiour, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="prayer">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:173418:44"/>
               <head>5. A more particular <hi>Morning Prayer on the</hi> beginning of a Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath day.</head>
               <p>MAnifold (O Lorde) are thy mercies, &amp; thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is infinite. In euery par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular which befalleth mee, I haue aboundant experience of thy loue. It is much (moſt gratious God) that I, which haue ſo many wayes prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked thee, ſhould bee let to liue, to behold the light and comfort of the day: But much more is it, that hauing béene hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a profaner of thy holy day, a barren and an hypocriticall
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:173418:45"/>
profeſſor of thy word, a fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and an vnprofitable hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, I ſhould yet enioy the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed opportunitie of another Sabaoth. How iuſtly mightſt thou long ſince haue fatted vp my heart and giuen mee ouer vnto a reprobate mind, taking from me the comfortable and happie freedome of going into thy houſe, and of giuing atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance vpon the poſtes of thy doores! O teach mee (I pray theée) to value thy mercy in this behalfe according to the true worth thereof: Suffer me not ſlightly to entertaine either this or any other of thy fauours. And, as thou haſt brought mee to the beginning
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:173418:45"/>
of this holy reſt: ſo enable me, (I beſéech thee) to thee ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying it, and to ſuch a kind of ſpending the ſame as thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireſt. Teach mee to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that it is thine owne ordinance, euen one of thoſe vnchangeable lawes, which thou wroteſt with thine owne finger, that this day ſhould af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a more ſpeciall manner be diuerted &amp; deuoted to thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, &amp; that thou haſt not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore reſtrained outward im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments in our callings be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe idelenes pleaſeth thee, or becauſe eaſe giuen vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſh is a part of thy worſhip; but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt in thy infinite wiſedome ſo appointed it, that being fréed
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:173418:46"/>
from all other encombrances, we might wholy apply our ſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ues, eyther to the publique or priuate exerciſes of godlineſſe Giue mee therefore grace (I moſt humbly entreat thee) that I may call thy Sabbaoth a de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>light to conſecrate it as glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous vnto thee, and that I may beware of doing mine owne waies, or of ſéeking mine own will, or of ſpeaking vaine words, and may euen bind my ſelfe to a ſerious and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed courſe of ſeruing thée in the practiſe of ſuch dueties as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the hallowing of this day. I know (O Lord) that herein I ſhall méet with many lets; mine owne corrupt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:173418:46"/>
will repine &amp; thinke this a yoke and a burden that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be endured: abroad in the world, I ſhall ſée many vaine faſhions, followed by great troupes, making thy day a day of carnal pleaſure; I ſhall be derided and ſcorned, if I refuſe to doe as others doe. I ſhal méet alſo with many cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning perſwaders, which will ſéeke by plauſible reaſons to draw mee from diligence and conſtancy in this courſe. O Lorde (I beſéech thée) euen with the bowing of my heart, to make me ſtrong againſt all theſe withdrawments: Grant that I may more eſtéeme obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to thee, then either the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:173418:47"/>
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenting of mine own ſenſual affections, or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> auoyding of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proche amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g profane perſons, or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſatiſfying of men; be their pretenſes, what they may be. I am taught (O Lord) &amp; I do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue it, that thy yoke is eaſie, &amp; that thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements are not grieuous: &amp; I know that by a holy vſe in theſe religious ſeruices, I ſhall make them ſo familiar vnto me, &amp; ſhall alſo find that excéeding ſwéetnes in them, that I ſhal euen long for thy Sabaoth before it comes, &amp; the time will ſéeme ſhort vnto me that is ſo beſtowed. And for this day (moſt louing Father) I pray thee bleſſe vnto me the particular buſineſſes thereof.
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:173418:47"/>
In praying, giue me reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to thy Maieſtie, ſenſe of my own wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, fayth in thy promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, freſh remembrance of thy former kindneſſes, charitable &amp; compaſſionate &amp; yéelding affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions towards others. In hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring vouchſafe mee an vnloc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked &amp; an vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding heart, a right iudgement, meekenes of ſpirit, liuelines of affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of memory. In co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting at thy table, beſtow on me an hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bled ſoule, a hungring heart, a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience purged from dead workes, power of ſweet meditation vpon the death of Chriſt. In looking vpon the adminiſtration of Baptiſme, afforde mee mindfulneſſe of mine owne vowe, remorſe
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:173418:48"/>
for my often fayling in that ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne promiſe, earneſtneſſe of deſire for the good of the bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, ioy for the encreaſe of thy Church. In ſinging, take fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me all both dulnes and vanity, make me to ſing with a grace in my heart, ſtill ſtriuing to lift vp my ſoule vnto thee. En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large my heart towards o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as occaſion ſhall be offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that I may bee ready to giue to thoſe that want, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in euery good work, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable to the ſicke, tender hearted to thoſe whom thou haſt humbled, apt to make peace, where diſcord is. Let all workes of mercy bee a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light vnto me, and make mee
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:173418:48"/>
carefulll not to ſtay till I am prouoked, but to ſéeke occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to doe good. And when I am priuate (O Lord) ſanctifie my thoughts, that I may me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate in good things, and may hide thy worde in my ſecret parts, and may loue it, and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially that I may ſhewe the fruite of it in all my conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Finally, I humbly pray thee, ſo to guide me both in pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blique and priuate dutyes, that when it commeth to euening, I may féele my knowledge to be encreaſed, my fayth ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened, my ſoule &amp; conſcience abundantly refreſhed, and all this for Chriſt Ieſus his ſake, &amp; for thine owne Names ſake Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="prayer">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:173418:49"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>6. Another Prayer</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more ſpeciall, reſpecting the hearing of Gods word.</head>
               <p>ETernall God, moſt grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and mercifull in Ieſus Chriſt, euery good giuing &amp; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery perfect gift co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth down from thee: thou haſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if any man lacke wiſedome hee ſhould aſke of thee, &amp; thou haſt promiſed to deny nothing that is aſked of thee in thy Sons name; In obedience vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this thy commaundement, &amp; in aſſurance of thy readines to make good thy promiſe, I doe héere caſt downe my ſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee, praying thee, as at all other times, ſo now eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to be good vnto mee. I
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:173418:49"/>
am now (O Lord) by thy gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious prouidence, to bee a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of thy holy word, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching whereof is the ordinary meanes appointed by thee to ſaue my Soule, &amp; to draw me out of the power of ſatha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto thine own ſelfe. I, for my part, am vnworthy of ſo great a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour as to bee admitted to heare it, and I am euery way vnfit &amp; vnable to heare it with profit. My heart is ful of blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; ignorance, my affections are froward and vntractable. I am euen reprobate by nature vnto euery good duty: I am dul of hearing, ſlow of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceit, back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to entertaine, but apt to let ſlippe any good inſtruction.
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:173418:50"/>
I beſeech thee in Ieſus Chriſt, by the working of thy ſpirit, to reforme within mee theſe cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions: Make me as a new borne babe to deſire the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere milke of thy moſt ſacred word: graunt that I may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce at it, as one that findeth a great ſpoyle, let it bee better vnto me the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thouſands of gold and ſiluer; Open my heart, as thou didſt the heart of <hi>Lydia,</hi> that I may euen with a kinde of hunger and gréedineſſe at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend vnto the things which are deliuered: cleare the eyes of my mind, &amp; anoint them with that pretious ſalue of thy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that the ſcales of ignorance may fall from them, and that I
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:173418:50"/>
may ſée the wonders of thy Law, euen thy hid wiſedome, which my nature of it ſelfe is not able to diſcerne: And, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou haſt promiſed to guide the humble in thy way, and to reueale thy ſecret to the méeke, take from mee, I pray thee, a proud heart, teach mée to become a foole in my ſelfe, that I may bee wiſe in thee: Suffer me not to meaſure the myſteries of thy kingdome by mine owne blind reaſon and corrupt affection; but giue me grace to deny my ſelfe, and to labour to bring mine owne thoughts into captiuity vnder Chriſt, that I may not dare to oppoſe mine owne conceipts
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:173418:51"/>
and fancies vnto the maieſtie of thy trueth reuealed in thy word. Giue vnto the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, a doore of vtterance, that he may open his mouth boldly to publiſh the ſecret of thy Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel. Direct his tongue that he may ſpeak vnto my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, &amp; that if there bee any cloſe cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lurking in me (as Lord, who can vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d his faults) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſearching power of thy word may diſcouer it, and rip it vp e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the very bottome. And vouchſafe vnto me that meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſpirit, and ſuch calme and yéelding affections, that I may not repine nor mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mure at reproofe, but may loue him rather that rebuketh,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:173418:51"/>
and may take it as a ſpeciall fauour fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee, that I am not ſuffered to go on in ſin, nor gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ouer to mine own corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. In euery point of holy doctrine taught me, make me to remember who it is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth by the mouth of man, that I may receiue the worde as a meſſage from thee, whether it be comfort, or reproofe, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; ſo may giue it y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; that awful reſpect which is due vnto thy holy Orac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s: And becauſe (O Lord) as I am naturally forgetfull, ſo the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill watcheth to catch away the worde as ſoone as it is deliuered, therefore I pray thee to ſtabliſh my memorie
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:173418:52"/>
that I may hold faſt thy bleſſed trueth, and may alwayes haue it in ſtore againſt the time of néed. To this end, make mée carefull in the vſe of all good priuate meanes, ſuch as are Prayer, meditation, confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence with others as occaſion ſhall require. Beget in mée a godly diſcretion, that I may diligently ſearch the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, whether the things I heare, are ſo, and may try all things; neither raſhly reiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, nor ſuddenly belieuing whatſoeuer is deliuered. And when I haue found thy trueth, ſo ſtabliſh my heart, that I may not wauer nor be caryed about with euery wind of doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:173418:52"/>
but may continue in the things which I haue learned, labouring daily to bee led for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward vnto more perfection. And ſéeing, hearing and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing without practiſe doe but encreaſe vnto more condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, therefore (O Lord) do thou ſo water that which I heare, with thy heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly deaw, that it may bring foorth much fruit in my life, &amp; that I maybe a credite to my profeſſion, and no diſgrace nor ſlander to thy trueth: Grant all theſe things for thy deare Sons ſake Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, to whom with thee &amp; thy bleſſed Spirit, I deſire to aſcribe all honour and glory now and for euer. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="prayer">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:173418:53"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>7. Another of the like</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, reſpecting the Sacrament of the Lordes Supper.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> Am taught (O Lorde) that without thee I can doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and that all mine en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauours are in vaine with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thy bleſſing. In due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard whereof, I am become an humble ſuter vnto thy ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, that thou wouldeſt bée pleaſed to proſper and to direct my preſent purpoſe of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating at thy table. It is thy will that I ſhould often come vnto this holy banquet, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtrengthening my fayth, &amp; for the preſeruation of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:173418:53"/>
of Chriſtes death. O Lord, ſtrike my heart with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence vnto it as vnto thy or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, and as to a feaſt to which thou haſt tyed thy more eſpeciall preſence, that I may not dare to preſſe in before thee vnprepared. Before I come, teach me to grow into a very ſtrict examinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of mine own Soule, that I may ſée how I haue liued, &amp; in what meaſure I am furniſhed for ſo waighty a ſeruice. And, becauſe I know that the more I looke into my ſelfe, the more I ſhall ſée mine owne nakedneſſe and defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, therefore I pray thee to ſupply mee from thy infinite fulneſſe; Giue mee a through
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:173418:54"/>
vnderſtanding of the miſerie of my eſtate, who am by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture a childe of wrath as well as others. Make me to ſée the hainouſneſſe of thoſe innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable euils and groſſe ſinnes which I haue multiplyed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee from time to time; nay, which I haue runne into ſince my laſt preſenting my ſelfe before thee at thy board, when I promiſed better obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. O cauſe my ſtony heart to bléede within mee, when I thinke vpon mine owne ſcant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in good dutyes and vpon my delight and forwardneſſe to tranſgreſſe. Make me to be aſhamed and euen confounded in my ſelf for thoſe many enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:173418:54"/>
which fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my corrupt and vnreformed heart doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually breake foorth into my outward man, euery member being a very weapon of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe to doe ſeruice vnto ſathan. Thus (O Lord) ſhall thy mercyes in Chriſt be ſwéet vnto me, &amp; I ſhall come with an hungring and thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting ſoule vnto thy table. And I pray thee to encreaſe in mée that gift of fayth, that I may both come to this thine ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance with a deſire to enlarge it, and may alſo féele it to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue ſtrength and growth of aſſurance of mine owne perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and particular intereſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death of Chriſt. Remooue
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:173418:55"/>
farre from mee all ſwelling, diſdainefull and vncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble affections: O Lorde, this is a feaſt of loue, and to it a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious and a reuengeful heart can be no welcome gueſt. And when I haue preſented my ſelfe at thy table, I beſéech thee to reſtraine my idle and gad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thoughts, drawe them to the earneſt &amp; ſerious meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that which is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> life of the Sacrament, the death of my Sauiour. Rauiſh my Soule with the admiratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his loue, that ſhould giue himſelfe to dy for me a moſt vile, vnworthy and ſinfull creature. Stirre mee vppe, euen to vowe and conſecrate my ſelfe for euer
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:173418:55"/>
vnto him that hath vouchſafed himſelfe to bée a ſacrifice for mée. And after I haue receiued theſe pledges of thy loue, and ſeales of thy fauour in thy deareſt Sonne, O make me truely thankefull to thy maieſtie, and carefull both at the preſent, and euer after, to ſhew foorth the fruits of thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe in an holy and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous conuerſation, to thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, the good of others, and mine owne eternall comfort in Ieſus Chriſt my Sauiour. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="prayer">
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:173418:56"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>8. Preſently after</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing, before the Thankeſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing <hi>by the whole Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation,</hi> a man may ſecretly lift vp his ſoule on this faſhion.</head>
               <p>AFfect my heart (O Lorde) with this eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of thy loue, teach me in it to ſée the riches of thy grace, who art pleaſed for my weakenes ſake by ſuch familiar meanes to figure out before me, and to ſeale vp vnto my ſoule, a treaſure of that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite worth, as is thy fauour in Ieſus Chriſt. O that I may as ſenſibly féele his death to be ſwéet vnto my Soule, as I do
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:173418:56"/>
theſe creatures of bread and wine, to afford a pleaſing taſte and refreſhing to my body. O Lord euermore giue mee ſuch a féeling. And now (O hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Father) ſuffer mee not to depart hence forgetfull of thy kindneſſe: but graunt that I may now at this inſtant e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen couenant with mine own ſoule, to walke in a better courſe of holy obedience then heretofore, reſpecting all thy commandements, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouring alwayes to haue a cleare conſcience before thee &amp; before all men; that ſo glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying thee in this life, I may be glorified with thee in thy king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom through Ieſus Chriſt. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="prayer">
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:173418:57"/>
               <head>9. A Prayer for the afflicted <hi>in what kind ſoeuer.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Gratious God, how hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py am I, who haue ſuch a ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g tower as thy great name to run vnto, eſpecially now in this ſad &amp; heauy day of tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? I ſée (O Lord) by conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall experience, that the help of man is vaine, and that all earthly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tentments, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the flattering ſhewe they make, yet are but as a ſtaffe of réede, vpon which if a man leane, it will runne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his hand and pearce it. If I turne mee to my auncient lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers and friendes, it may bee they will ſtand aſide from my plague, &amp; mine olde acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:173418:57"/>
wil hide themſelues, and I ſhal be euen as a ſtranger in the ſight of my familiars: If I ſéeke to my neighbours. alas, what refreſhing ſhall I finde? Trueth it is (O God) &amp; thou haſt ſo ordayned, that he which is in miſery ſhould be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forted by his neighbor: but men haue forſaken y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feare of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; ſo that hee, which is ready to fall, is as a deſpiſed lampe, and few are apt to wéepe with him that is in trouble: Beſides, the greateſt part are ſo ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come with groſſe ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they are miſerable co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forters &amp; phyſicia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of no value, not able to miniſter a worde in time to him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is weary. Whither then, or
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:173418:58"/>
to whom ſhall I goe but vnto thee (O moſt gratious &amp; ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Father)? Thou art a piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full God, thy compaſſions are great, thou art the Father of mercies, &amp; the God of all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, thou makeſt the wound, and bindeſt it vp, thou ſmiteſt, &amp; thy hands doe make whole, thou haſt commaunded to call vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee in the day of trouble, and thou art a helpe ready to be found. To thee, therefore do I lift vp my ſoule: Encline thine eare (O Lord) and heare, open thine eyes (O Lord) and ſée, look mercifully vpon thine afflicted ſeruant: the dayes of ſorow are come vpon me, euen changes &amp; armies of miſeries
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:173418:58"/>
are againſt me. If my griefe were waighed, it would bee heauier then the ſand of the ſea; I am broken with one breaking vpon another. Make me (I pray thee) to conſider ſeriouſly, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou which haſt done all this, that theſe things come not by chaunce, but by thy prouidence and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine appointment, that ſo I may be dumme and not open my mouth to murmure or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine. Open mine eyes that I may ſée mine owne deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings, and what cauſe I haue giuen thee euen to cruſh me to pieces with thy heauy iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, yea to cauſe the pit of thy eternall vengeance to ſhut
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:173418:59"/>
her mouth vpon me. What cauſe haue I left vnto mee to complaine, when I am leſſe then thy ſmalleſt mercy, and my ſins greater then the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſorrow thou haſt layd vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me? It is thy loue (O Lorde) from whence this proceedeth. In this courſe, thou doeſt offer thy ſelf vnto me as to a ſonne: thou knoweſt my corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, the rebellion of my heart, the crookedneſſe &amp; vnreformednes of my nature, thou ſéeſt before ſome great euill that I am like to fall into, if I bee left vnto mine owne courſe, thou fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt me to be forgetfull of my duety to thee, cold in Prayer, backward and lumpiſh in holy
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:173418:59"/>
ſeruices, well-néere lulled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſléepe in the common ſecurity of the times: It is thy wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to rouſe me vp, &amp; to put thy hooke of affliction into my noſtrils, to bring mee backe into that good way from which I am falling. I knowe thou doeſt therfore chaſten me, that I may not be condemned with the world. O teach me (I pray thee) to learne to iudge my ſelfe, to ſearch &amp; to try my wayes, to pry into my courſe by-paſt, that I may finde out thoſe euils which beare in mée the greateſt ſway, and may in ſome meaſure vnderſtande, what it is which thou aymeſt at in afflicting mee.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:173418:60"/>And enable mee withall to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme mine errors, to recouer my wandring, &amp; to get a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie victorie ouer my rebellious fleſh: that I may be able to ſay hereafter, It is good for mee that I was in trouble, bleſſed be the time that the Lorde af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted me; and how ſweet is the quiet fruite of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe which ſpringeth foorth from the bitter roote of tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation? In the meane ſpace (O Lord) vntill it ſhall pleaſe thée to put an ende to my preſent grieuaunces, teach me, not to make haſte, or to ſéeke by vile and vnwarrantable courſes to wind my ſelf out of thy hands, but graunt that I may tarry
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:173418:60"/>
thy leaſure with patience, not daring to preſcribe vnto thee what to doe. And when this ſtorme is ouer, and the ſorrowe paſt O kéepe me from ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, make me to remember the vowes and promiſes of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence which I now make vnto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hee prepare mee to a freſh tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, that my care may be to bée prouided for whatſoeuer thy pleaſure ſhall bee to lay vpon me. Heare mee in this, and in all other my ſuites, for his ſake in whom thou art beſt pleaſed, euen Ieſus Chriſt the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. Amen.</p>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:173418:61"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:173418:61"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="prayer">
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:173418:62"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>13. A Prayer, in</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of ſome loſſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, as of honour, or goods, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Eternall God, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> God of prouidence, the orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer and the diſpoſer of all things both in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and in earth: Be ready (I beſéech thee) to heare the Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of thy diſtreſſed ſeruaunt. Helpe my weakenes (I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat thée) and quicken mee to the performance of this duety of calling vpon thy Name. I am eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aſhamed of my ſelf, to ſée mine owne faintnes, &amp; how
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:173418:62"/>
ſoone I am caſt downe vpon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery occaſion. O rayſe me vp (I pray thee) and make me to lift my heart towards thee, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to whoſe good pleaſure all things come to paſſe: Is it not thou (O Lord) which haſt laid theſe things vpon me? art not thou he who both giueſt &amp; takeſt at thy will? art not thou the iudge which makeſt low &amp; which makeſt high? ſhall I murmure againſt thee, which haſt ſuch an abſolute &amp; vncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troulable ſoueraingty ouer al? ſhal I receiue good at thy hand, and not euill? O kéepe downe my repining &amp; mutinous and diſcontented thoughts, allay y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:173418:63"/>
height and hautineſſe of my ſpirit, teach me how to be aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed &amp; to haue want, make mée to ſée the vanitie of that which I was wont euen to admire, and to ſet my heart vpon. Let this abridgement be a ſchoole maſter vnto mee, that I may learne by it to draw mine affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions from theſe fading and tranſitorie commodities. O Lord, what is honour? Is it not a blaſt, or as ſmoke which quickely vaniſheth? What is wealth? Is it not lighter then vanitie it ſelfe? doth it not take her to her wings as an Eagle and flye into the heauen? O knit my heart henceforth vnto thee: O bleſſed Father, faſten
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:173418:63"/>
my affections on the things which are aboue where Chriſt ſitteth at thy right hand: make mée to lay vp treaſure in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, &amp; to ſeeke after that king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of thine, which cannot be ſhaken: frame my heart to the choyce of the better part, of which I can neuer bee depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. Let mee affect the true honour which ſtandes in the faythfull ſeruice of my ſauior. Let me labor for that enduring and durable riches, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtes in the knowledge of thee, and in the féeling of thy grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſauour. Suffer me not (I pray thee) ſo to limit thy pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, as to thinke that thou art not now able to ſupply mée,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:173418:64"/>
ſith the meanes which I was wont to enioy is taken from mée; but make mee faythfully to conſider, that thy hand is not ſhortened, but that thou haſt inough in ſtore for thoſe that loue thee. Thou art able to giue me a great deale more, &amp; after thou haſt exerciſed mée awhile, to bleſſe my laſt dayes with more abundance then the firſt: thou canſt make the little meale in the barrell not to waſte, and the ſmall quantitie of oyle not to diminiſh: thou canſt cauſe a ſmall thing to bée better vnto mee then great ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches to the mightie, and a din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of greene hearbes to bée more ſauory to me, then a ſtal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:173418:64"/>
Oxe to them. O there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I beſéech thee, reſtrayne my deſires, make me willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to ſubmit my ſelfe to thy wiſedom; Let thy prouidence &amp; promiſe bee my ſtore-houſe, and the ſtocke that I rely vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to: let this ſatiſfy mée, that though I loſe all that I haue, yet inaſmuch as thou haſt once loued mée in Chriſt, I ſhall neuer loſe thy fauour. And let not the beholding of my children &amp; family diſharten mee, or make mee to caſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rils, and to ſay, <hi>Wherewith ſhall I feed them? How ſhall I clothe them?</hi> O Lord they are better then many ſpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:173418:65"/>
and dearer vnto thee then the lylies of the fielde; thy promiſe of mercy is entayled to my poſterity: O let my faith reſt vpon this foundation. Prepare me (I pray thee) to further trials, make mée ready by degrées to loſe euen my life it ſelfe, if it may be for thy glory. And thus (O Lord) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring to recko<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euen this croſſe (though my vnreformed na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture doeth gaineſay it) among thy chiefeſt fauours, I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend my ſelfe and my poore Prayers vnto thee in Chriſt Ieſus thy beloued Sonne, and my belieued ſauiour. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="prayer">
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:173418:65"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>11. A Prayer, fitted to the</hi> loſſe of an eſpeciall friend, as a Father or Huſband, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Almightie Lord God, whoſe glory is aboue the heauens, and which haſt thy dwelling on high, but yet abaſeſt thy ſelfe to behold the things in the earth, be pleaſed, euen for thy deareſt Sonnes ſake, to caſt down thy compaſſionate eye vpon my afflicted &amp; grieued caſe. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort (Lorde) comfort (I pray thee) thy ſeruants ſoule, ſuffer me not to be ſwallowed vp of diſcouragement. Thou haſt taken from mee the very ſtaffe
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:173418:66"/>
of mine eſtate, one, vpon who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (in the ey of fleſh &amp; blood) al my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort did depend; He is now gone y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way of all fleſh, &amp; hath made his bed in the darke: yet y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> (O Lord) ſtill liueſt, thou art alwayes the ſame, &amp; thy yeares ſhal not fayle. O rayſe vp (I beſéech thée) my languiſhing &amp; diſcouraged heart, my drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping thoughts: make mee to looke towards thee, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whom alone all comfort commeth. Haſt thou done this, &amp; ſhall I controule it? Is death thy meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger, and ſhal I murmure at his comming? Is my deareſt friend, whom I loued as mine own hart, gathered vnto thee, his appointed moneths being
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:173418:66"/>
now expired, &amp; ſhall I lament his happines? Doeſt thou ſtill hold me with thy hand, &amp; euen co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſe me about with thy gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious prouidence, &amp; ſhall I di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt? Is thy purpoſe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe &amp; power to be my God, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame yet that it was, &amp; ſhall I be doubtfull, as though I had made fleſh mine arme, or as if y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> (O alſufficient God) wert tyed vnto outward meanes? Muſt not I alſo ere it bee long make y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> graue my houſe, &amp; lye down with others in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> duſt? Is there not an aſſured hope y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> liue &amp; dye in the Lord Ieſus, ſhall bee ioyned together after death, and at the laſt day bée caught vppe in the cloudes
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:173418:67"/>
to méet the Iudge in the ayre, and after that to bee euer with the Lord! I moſt earneſtly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſéech the therefore (O my moſt gratious God) to moderate my paſſionate and vnrulely thoughts, to bring my violent affections into a holy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſe: Let me not be ſorrowfull like thoſe which haue no hope, make me to reioyce on his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, whoſe pilgrimage is at end, and whoſe Chriſtian and holy cauſe doeth euen aſſure mee, that thou haſt receiued him into euerlaſting habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Teach me to haue a holy and prepared longing for the day of my diſſolution: And graunt me that grace and wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:173418:67"/>
ſo to loue thoſe whome both Nature and Religion bind me to reſpect, that I may alwayes conforme and ſubmit my affections to thy moſt wiſe and ſoueraigne diſpoſings. To bee without apprehenſion of ſuch loſſes, I know by thy word, that it is impious; to bée extreame &amp; without meaſure in paſſion, is deſperate: Kéepe me, I beſéech thée, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meane, that my ſorrowes may bée tempered with comfort, &amp; my heart may alwayes bee fixed ſurely vpon thee: Afford mée both this and all other néedfull fauours in and for the merites of my alone Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="prayer">
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:173418:68"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>12. A Prayer applyed to the ſtate</hi> of a man inwardly perplext with the horror of ſin, with doubtings of Gods fauour, &amp; with the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of ſathan tending to deſpaire.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Thou moſt pitifull God, &amp; to thoſe who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou loueſt in Ieſus Chriſt, moſt tender Father, neuer did there any poore chaſed Hart bray after the riuers of water, ſo as my diſtreſſed and amazed Soule panteth after thee. Oh that I had fayth to lay holde vpon that moſt ſwéet promiſe, by which thou calleſt all that are weary and laden to come vnto thee. Faine I would (O Lord) approche into thy gratious
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:173418:68"/>
preſence, and happy ſéeme I to my ſelfe, if I might taſte though but (as it were) ſome crummes of thy rich mercy. Mee thinketh that all thinges which I ſée in the world and which the ſonnes of men doe dote vpon ſo exceedingly, are but dung and droſſe in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of thy fauour: Oh that I might be but one of the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of ſaints, or (as it were) a ſeruitor or doore kéeper among thy holy ones. Thus I ſée thy mercy, I admire it, I prefer it in my choyſe before the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt treaſure: but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I would apply it to my own particular caſe, Oh what a world of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courageme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts do I méet with?
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:173418:69"/>
My ſinnes doe take ſuch holde vpon me, that I am not able to looke vppe: they are ſo many, yea more in number then the hayres of my head, that my heart doth euen fayle mee to conſider them. When I think how my Soule and Spirit is fraughted &amp; defiled euen with whole millions of profane, hardened, ſecure, vicious, worldly &amp; vnſanctified thoghts, how many offers of grace I haue neglected, how thy for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance hath béene abuſed by mee, how I haue béene a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach and ſlaunder to thy Goſpel, how dead and lumpiſh and falſe-hearted I haue béene in thy ſeruice, how barren in
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:173418:69"/>
good workes, and what little procéedings I haue made, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rather backward then ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vnto more perfection, how I haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tented my ſelfe with ſhewes of godlineſſe: when (I ſay) I thinke vpon theſe and other my groſſe and palpable enormities, I cannot but vtterly condemne my ſelf, neither can I belieue that it is poſſible for ſo vile a wretch as I, to bee admitted into thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour. Sometimes I conceiue ſome litle hope, and I ſéeme to my ſelfe to haue ſome taſte of thy fauour, and ſome kinde of aſſurance that I am deare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thée in thy Sonne; but ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly my comfort vaniſheth,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:173418:70"/>
my hope is ouerclouded with perplexed doubtings, and I am well-neere ſwallowed vp with meere deſpaire. Can a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny mortal man (think I) know the mind of God: or if ſome ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſon may be ſo farre gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, as to vnderſtand Gods purpoſe touching himſelfe; is it poſſible that ſo vile a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as I, ſhoulde come to ſuch a high prerogatiue? Can the Spirit of the Lord, dwell in ſuch a ſtinking and polluted ſoule as mine? will hee vouchſafe to giue mee an aſſurance of Gods fauour? Or if I might knowe nowe that I am in the ſtate of grace, what aſſuraunce can I haue,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:173418:70"/>
that I ſhall ſo continue, being beſet with manie imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? Thus (O Lord) mine owne thoughts oppreſſe mee, and mine own ſoule doth plead the caſe againſt it ſelfe: Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is Sathan, the auncient e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy of thine Elect, wanting, to adde affliction to my mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie.</p>
               <p>Heeretofore his manner hath beene, to incite and to prouoke mee vnto ſinne, by hyding and couering the vg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and moſt loatheſome face thereof, and to beare mee in hand, that it was a verie ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie thing to repent, and that alſo thy fauour (O Lorde) might be procured by and by:
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:173418:71"/>
Now hee enlargeth my euils, &amp; makes my ſins to appeare before my conſcience in moſt terrible and hideous ſhapes; he telleth me, that my hypocriſie is apparant, that the guile of my heart is written in great letters and cannot bee denyed, that it is now in vaine for mee to ſue for grace, there being no hope of mercy left for ſuch of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendours: that it is to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe for mee to pray; for as I can not pray as I ſhould, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe then in hypocriſie, ſo neither (if I could pray aright) can there bee any acceſſe vnto the throne of grace for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts of ſuch a treſpaſſer. Notwithſtanding (O moſt
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:173418:71"/>
gracious God) euen in deſpite of his ſuggeſtions and amidſt all thoſe diſcouragements which mine own heart muſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth againſt mee. I doe héere aduenture my ſelfe into thy moſt glorious preſence; If I ſhall find fauour in thine eyes, ſhew me the light of thy coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance and I ſhall bee ſafe: If thou ſay, <hi>I haue no delight in thee,</hi> behold, héere I am, do to me as ſéemeth good in thine owne eyes. I knowe what thou haſt ſpoken in thy worde, namely: that if I draw néere vnto thee, thou wilt drawe néere vnto mee, and that thou wilt fulfill the deſires, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnexpreſſeable grones
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:173418:72"/>
and ſighings of thy ſeruants: Trueth it is (O Lord) I dare not ſay that I draw néere vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee as I ſhould, or that my deſires are ſuch as they ought to be, or that I groane vnder my ſinnes with ſuch an effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and pearcing féeling as is fit.</p>
               <p>All that I am able to doe, and that in much weakeneſſe, is to cry fayntly vnto thee, <hi>Oh draw mee, and I will runne after thee,</hi> make mee to deſire thy mercy in ſinceritie, bruiſe my heart, that it may yeeld out many vndiſſembled ſighings after thee. Yet (O Lorde) though there bee in mee but ſuch poor beginnings of grace,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:173418:72"/>
ſuffer me not (I beſéech thee) to caſt away my confidence. I am well aſſured that thou haſt not forgotten y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> promiſe of not breaking the bruiſed réede, nor putting out the ſmoking flaxe, and of giuing a bleſſing vnto thoſe which hunger after righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe.</p>
               <p>Is it poſſible (O Lorde) that thou ſhouldeſt leaue off to bee gracious, and ſhut vppe thy tender mercies in diſpleaſure? Didſt not thou ſend thy ſonne into the world to dye euen for chiefe ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners? Is it not true, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſinne abounds, there thy grace abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth much more?
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:173418:73"/>
Could I euer ſo much as tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie deſire reconciliation with th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e vnleſſe thou didſt worke it in me? Is not this requeſt, <hi>Lord, helpe my vnbeliefe,</hi> the very voyce of thy ſpirit with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in me? Could I complaine of the hardneſſe of my heart, or ſincerely lothe mine owne cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions as being diſpleaſing to thy maieſtie, if thine owne finger had not effected it? Should I féele ſuch a combate in my Soule, &amp; ſuch a tumult within me, if thou hadſt not truely begun to draw mee to thy ſelfe? Would ſathan ſo continually moleſt me, and ſo egerly purſue me with variety of moſt malicious and ſharpe
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:173418:73"/>
aſſaults, if I were ſtill held captiue by him at his will? Rayſe me vppe therefore (O Lord) I pray thee, refreſh my deiected and caſt downe ſoule, perfit the work of grace which thou haſt begun within mee, make mee to heare of ioy and gladnes, that the bones which thou haſt broken may reioyce. Thou haſt ſet me as a marke vnto thy ſelfe, thou haſt writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten bitter things againſt mee, and made mee to poſſeſſe my former iniquities, thou haſt hidden thy face from me, and taken me for thine enemy: co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort me now according to the dayes that thou haſt afflicted me, let mee behold thy face in
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:173418:74"/>
righteouſneſſe, and reſtore vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to me the ioy of thy ſaluation. Rebuke ſathan, I moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bly beſéech thee: though thou pleaſe to buffet mee with his meſſengers, yet let thy grace be ſufficient for me, and make thine owne power in reuiuing mee, perfect and manifeſt by my weakenes, which of it ſell is ready to bee preſſed downe with euery tentation. Giue mee that holy wiſedome, not to belieue ſathan, no, though he ſpeake the trueth; inaſmuch as he is the father of lyes, and neuer ſpeaketh trueth but for a wicked purpoſe. And (O Lorde) as thou encreaſeſt my comfort, ſo withall encreaſe
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:173418:74"/>
my care, that I may not fall from perplexitie to ſecuritie, but that I may alwayes keep my heart with all diligence, proouing my fayth, and ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching my wayes, and exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing my ſelfe vnto godlineſſe. Make mee a carefull and an vnderſtanding hearer of thy word, ſith it is the word of life, a quickening word, a worde which doeth reioyce the heart; and becauſe, except that be my delight, I ſhall vtterly periſh in mine afflictions.</p>
               <p>Make mee circumſpect to preuent ſinne, and fearefull ouer my ſelfe, that ſinne may not grow ſtrong vpon me: and graunt that I may ſtudy to
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:173418:75"/>
preſerue the peace of my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience aboue all things, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king héed of wounding it with preſumptuous ſinnes. And (O Lord) ſtabliſh me with thy frée ſpirit, that albeit ſathan ſéeke to ſift me &amp; to winnow me as wheat, yet my faith may ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer fayle, but may be as mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Zio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be remooued, but remaineth for euermore. Thus (O my gracious God) hauing, through thy mercy, peace in belieuing, and ioy in thy holy ſpirit, I ſhal finiſh my courſe in comfort: which I pray thee graunt mee for his ſake who is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prince of peace, euen Ieſus Chriſt, to whom with thee and the holy Ghoſt,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:173418:75"/>
bée all honour and glory, now and for euer. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="prayer">
               <head>
                  <hi>13. A Prayer, then</hi> needfull, when a man hath ſome ſpeciall combate with ſome one or moe ſpecial ſinnes, againſt which hee deſireth victory.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Louing Father in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thee of thine abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant mercie to giue leaue to euery humbled &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed ſinner, to pour out his Soule before thee, and thou haſt bound thy ſelfe by a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe both to heare and to helpe all thoſe which ſéeke thée with an vnfained heart; The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:173418:76"/>
aſſura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce hereof hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me courage (albeit moſt vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>worthy) to preſent my ſelf here before thee, &amp; to conceiue hope y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou wilt not ſend me empty away. Wounded (O Lord) I am with mine owne hainous ſins, my vntamed fleſh doth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes rebel &amp; luſt againſt my ſpirit: ſome good motions and purpoſes I ſometimes haue, but (alas) they are quickely quenched, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of my mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers ſo preuaileth, that I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not do y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good which I would. I haue in me (I confeſſe) the ſéed of euery ſin, &amp; my nature is apt to be wrought vnto any kind of euill. But (O God) there are ſome principall cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:173418:76"/>
which do beare in me y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greateſt ſway, &amp; they do ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen raign in my mortal body, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I am forced to obey them in the luſts therof: The deuil alſo is ful of moſt malicious policie &amp; he ſtill worketh vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all adua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages, &amp; out of al things almoſt taketh occaſion to adde fuel to my wicked deſires, &amp; by plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing &amp; delightful baites to lead them on vnto a helliſh perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The more I ſtriue, the ſtronger (mee thinketh) theſe corruptions grow: which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth me to feare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vtter quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of thy gracrs, &amp; the grie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uing of thy holy ſpirit. Hereby my Prayers are interrupted, my meditations perplexed, and
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:173418:77"/>
robbed of their wonted ſwéet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, my hearing and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of thy word is made vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable: My fayth is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countred with grieuous doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, becauſe I cannot féele that ſtrength and power of thy ſpirit which I would. O Lord, if thy mercy be not my ſtay, I muſt néedes bee ouercome: whom haue I in Heauen but thee? whither ſhall I fly but to thy gracious aſſiſtance? I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſéech thee, to haue compaſſion on me, crucifie and kill theſe vnruly luſts, abate y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtrength of theſe violent and wicked de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires: Weaken them, I pray thee, &amp; ſuffer them not to haue dominion ouer mee. Let thy
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:173418:77"/>
Spirit guide me, and lead mee into the land of righteouſneſſe. Or if it bee thy pleaſure (O Lord) ſtill to exerciſe me, yet leaue me not deſtitute of thy grace, but encreaſe it in mee, that I may grow vnto a lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger meaſure of ſanctification: Make me hereby the more fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent and frequent in Prayer, the more ſtrait to preuent all occaſions leading vnto euill, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more ielous ouer my wayes, the more humble and vile in mine owne ſight: that ſo euen out of euill there may ſpring good vnto me, &amp; that I may ſée the fulfilling of that holy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, that all things worke to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether for the beſt vnto thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants.
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:173418:78"/>
Heare me (I entreate thee) in this, and in all other my requeſts, for Chriſt Ieſus ſake thy beſt beloued Sonne, and the onely ſauiour of thy choſen. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="prayer">
               <head>
                  <hi>14. A Prayer of Humiliation</hi> and ſorrow, after ſome ſpecial ſinne committed.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> My God, I am aſhamed and confounded to lift vp mine eyes vnto thee: mine ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities are encreaſed ouer my head, and my treſpaſſes are growne vp vnto the heauen. I muſt néedes wonder at thy great forbearance, that I am not euen ſwallowed vppe or ſwept away with ſome extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. And now
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:173418:78"/>
(O Lord) eſpecially, hauing ſo groſly ſinned againſt thee, and done ſo great an euill in thy ſight; How haue I (vile wretch y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I am) wounded my owne conſcience? How haue I laid my ſelf open to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> malice &amp; miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief of the diuel? What a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace &amp; ſlander haue I broght vpon my profeſſion? What an offence &amp; ſcandal haue I giuen vnto others? What a ioy will this be to the wicked, that they haue now by me gotten ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to ſpeak euil of? But (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all O Lord) how haue I diſhonoured thee, whoſe fauors haue bin ſo many &amp; ſo continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all towards me? I know not with what names &amp; tearms to ſet out my ſin, ſufficient to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pres the hainous &amp; hideous na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:173418:79"/>When I thinke vpon thy pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, vpon the meanes of grace which thou haſt affor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded me, vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> light of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge which thou haſt giuen me, vpon the good motions, (as it were ſo many gracious ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſements) which thou haſt from time to time, ſtirred vp in me, vpon the profeſſion which I make, vpon the ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry promiſes &amp; vowes of bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter obedience with which I haue tied my ſelfe vnto thy Maieſtie, vpon the diuers ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions which (by thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence I knowe) haue béene vſed to mee by thy ſeruaunts, purpoſely to preuent and to ſtoppe this euil in me, me thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:173418:79"/>
I may call it rebellion (which is as the ſin of witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft) or preſumption in the higheſt degrée. And yet (O Lord) I féele ſuch a benum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medneſſe to créepe vpon mée, ſuch a hardned cruſt to growe vpon my ſecret parts, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit I ſée my ſinne, and knowe it to be excéeding great, neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe I cannot ſo bemone it, ſo lament it, ſo grieue for it, ſo deteſt &amp; abhorre it, as I ſhould. Smite (O gracious God) ſmite, I beſéech thée my flinty heart, make it euen to melt within me, at the ſight of mine own tranſgreſſions; Settle in it y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> godly ſorrow, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth repentance vnto ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:173418:80"/>
Humble my ſoule vnder thy mightie hand, and ſuffer mee not to fréeze in the dregs of mine own corruptions. Make mine head full of water, and mine eyes a fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taine of teares which may runne downe, like a riuer, day and night: Oh let me take no reſt, nor ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the apple of mine eye to ceaſe: cauſe mee to powre out my heart like water before thy face, that I may by all meanes teſtifie the vnfayned griefe of my ſoule that I haue ſo diſpleaſed thee. And grant (O Lord) that I may not ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row ſo much becauſe of hell and condemnation which I haue made to be due vnto me,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:173418:80"/>
but that my chiefe vexation may bée to thinke how I haue abuſed thy mercy, and requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thy exceeding loue with ſo foule a treſpaſſe. Withall (O moſt gracious Father) ſéeing there is mercy with thee, and that thou haſt no deſire that the wicked ſhould dye, giue me leaue to become a ſufer vnto thy grace, not in mine owne name (for what am I that I ſhould preſſe into thy preſence?) but in the name of thy deareſt Sonne, the alone Mediatour, and the onely Peace-maker of his choſen. I moſt hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly beſéech thee for his ſake to haue mercy on me:
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:173418:81"/>
O Lord, a plaiſter of his blood ſhall be a moſt ſoueraigne me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine, to cure my running and rotten and feſtered ſore. His ſtripes &amp; wounds are of an healing nature: no ſope, nor nitre of mine owne tempering can purge away my filthines: onely his bloud hath that ſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring force, that it can make ſcarlet and crimſon ſinne as white as wooll. Oh then, I pray thee, waſh me throughly from mine iniquitie, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the multitude of thy compaſſions, cleanſe me from my ſin. Turne thy face from mee, and from my hatefull and enormous courſe, and look vpon the perfite and vnſpotted
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:173418:81"/>
righteouſnes of thy ſon. Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply my emptienes out of his infinite fulnes, the depth wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of cannot be fadomed, nor the ſtore thereof conſumed. Couer my vncleanneſſe with the rove of his holineſſe, euen with the garment of ſaluation, with which thou deckeſt and tireſt thine elect. And albeit I am of all others which either haue béene, are, or ſhall be, the moſt vnworthy: yet vouchſafe to certifie my Soule of thy grace &amp; fauor, by the ſecret teaching of thy holy Spirit, make me to féele inwardly the ioy of thy ſaluation, reſtore to mee that ſweet taſte of thy loue, which I was wont to haue, &amp; which
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:173418:82"/>
I now haue robbed my ſelfe of, by this my diſobedience to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thee. Let the apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of my ſinne bee tempered with a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable application of thy mercy, that I may hold an euen courſe betwixt feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ſecurity and faith-leſſe deſpaire; beholding at once, both my vilenes to humble me, &amp; the riches of thy grace to reuiue me. And, as an eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of thy loue in this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half, ſtrengthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me by thy grace to the making of the beſt vſe of mine owne corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: Grant that the thought of them may kill in me al pride of heart, and may make me to abaſe my ſelf and to become euen vile in my
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:173418:82"/>
own ſight; Gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t me to be here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the more watchfull ouer my courſe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more diligent to auoyd all inducements &amp; inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cements vnto theſe or the like euils, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more apt to be taught, the more willing to bee admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more forward to beg thy aſſiſtance, &amp; the more cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritably co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſionate towards others, rather pitying and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moaning and praying for, then cenſuring their infirmities. And (Lorde) ſuffer me not, I beſeech thee to ſatiſfie my ſelfe with this, that I haue once made ſome ſhew of humiliatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and ſorrow for my falles: but graunt, I may encreaſe in the performance of theſe duetyes, and may euery day renue &amp; enlarge my repentance for
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:173418:83"/>
particular ſlippes, growing ſtill into a deeper deteſtation of my ſins, and deſiring with more and more earneſtneſſe and ſtriuing, to bee renewed in the Spirit of my mind: that ſo being cleanſed from all fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe both of the fleſh and Spirit, I may growe vppe vnto full holineſſe in thy feare, through Ieſus Chriſt. In whoſe name only I commend vnto thee my requeſts, and for whoſe ſake thou haſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to deny nothing to thy ſeruants. So be it. <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="prayer">
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:173418:83"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>11. A Prayer in reſpect</hi> of death, needful at all times but eſpecially in ſickeneſſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> God, the God of the Spirits of all fleſh, and which haſt the keyes of hell and of death; thou haſt prepared them both, and thou ruleſt them both at thine owne pleaſure. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſéech thee bee mercifull to a poore trembling &amp; weak-hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſinner, and vouchſafe to preſerue mee from the horror and extreamitie of dread, into which I am euen now ready to fall. When I conſider (O Lord) how that I dwell in a
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:173418:84"/>
houſe of clay, my foundation being in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> duſt, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I muſt ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long make my bed in the dark, ſaying to corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>Thou art my Father,</hi> and to the worme, <hi>Thou art my Mother, &amp; my Siſter,</hi> O how my belly trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth, &amp; what a kind of rotten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth into my bones! my ſpirit ſeeming to fayle me, &amp; my heart within mee being filled with diſmayednes. Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially, when I thinke vpon the iudgement that commeth after it, &amp; the ſtraitneſſe of that account which I am inſtantly to be called to, and vpon thoſe euerlaſting chaynes vnder darkenes in which the wicked are reſerued vnto the laſt ſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:173418:84"/>
I am then ſo euen ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed with amazedneſſe, that I ſéeme to my ſelfe for the preſent, not to know where to find any true refreſhing. I am told by thy bleſſed and not-deceiuing word, that the ſting of death is mine owne ſinne, and with it I daily feele my ſelfe goared and galled and wounded ſo excéedingly, that (mée thinketh) to mee (poore wretch) there can be no hope of recouery, but death muſt néedes bée as a paſſage to leade mee into the bottomleſſe priſon of hell. Rayſe vp (O Lord I beſéech thée) theſe my ſad &amp; vnquiet thoughts, teach mee how to ouercome theſe
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:173418:85"/>
diſcouraging and killing per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexities, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death may not be vnto me as a king of fear: nor I, as one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked, whoſe hope doeth periſh with their breath, &amp; the candle of whoſe comfort is put out, when thou art pleaſed to take away their Soule Reuiue my memory, that I may call to minde, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortably ponder thoſe things which thy ſacred word hath taught me: namely, how the nature of death is cleane alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to thy ſeruants, the ſting is plucked out, &amp; it ſelfe is ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed vp in victory. To them the comming thereof ſhall be a time of diſcharge, they ſhall by it bee fréed from ſickneſſes
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:173418:85"/>
of body, from anguiſhes of ſpirit, from all poſſibilitie of ſinning againſt their God, from the tedious and diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenting ſocietie of the vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: their fleſh ſhall reſt in hope, their graues ſhall bee vnto them as beds of eaſe, being ſwéetened and ſeaſoned by the buriall of their Sauiour: the Angels ſhall giue attendance vpon their Soules, to conuey the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into <hi>Abrahams</hi> Boſome, to the fellowſhip of belieuers, to the ſpirits of iuſt and perfit men; ſo ſhall they bée with Chriſt: which is beſt of all. This (O Lorde) is the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth by death vnto thy choſen: Oh what are
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:173418:86"/>
all the moſt torturing ſickneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, the bitter pangs and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes of the graue, vnto ſuch a glorious exchange? Who would feare corruption, for a neuer ſading crowne of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe? What is a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentany yéelding of the body to conſumption in the duſt, in compariſon of the euerlaſting preſeruation of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Soule, with aſſurance alſo, that in the time appointed theſe vile bodyes ſhall by the mightie working of thy beloued Sonne, be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhioned like vnto his owne glorious body, and ſo both bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes and ſoules bee for euer with him in his kingdome.</p>
               <p>Teach mee (O Lord) effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:173418:86"/>
to apply theſe things to mine owne comfort, that ſo this timorouſneſſe procée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from the guilt of ſinne, may be turned into a chéere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full expectation, and euen a longing for the day of my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution.</p>
               <p>And, leſt I ſhould beguile my owne Soule, in laying clayme to that ſpirituall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing which belonges not to mee, make mee to labour for thoſe aſſured euidences and vndeceiuing fore-runners of a happy departure. I know (O Lorde) that if I liue héere without conſcience, I ſhall ſurely dye without comfort.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="138" facs="tcp:173418:87"/>Holineſſe here, is the way and path to future happineſſe. I muſt ſeeke to glorifie thee, if I deſire to be glorified with thée, I muſt fight the good fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſatha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, againſt the world, againſt mine owne corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I muſt faythfully fulfill my courſe, and performe the ſeruice to which thou haſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed me, I muſt know thy trueth, and keepe the faith in ſoundnes and ſinceritie to the end: otherwiſe it will bee in vaine to exſpect a crowne of righteouſneſſe. I muſt come to the firſt reſurrection, or elſe I ſhal neuer eſcape the ſecond death: Graunt mee therefore grace (I humbly pray thee)
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:173418:87"/>
to ſerue thee in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe all my dayes, and to endeauour alwayes to haue a cléere conſcience towards thee, and towards men; Kill my corruption in mee, that I may bee euen dead to ſinne, but aliue to thee in Ieſus Chriſt. And becauſe if I liue after the fleſh, taking thought for it to fulfill it, I ſhall dye; therefore, I beſéech thée, to mortifie the deedes of the body by thy ſpirit, that ſo I may haue my fruite in holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and my end eternall life. Teach mee often to number my dayes, and to conſider the vncertaine certaintie of my ende, that I may dye euen e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:173418:88"/>
day, ſtill looking and ſtill preparing for my change, and making account that each day may bee the day of my diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution. Strengthen alſo my weake and faint faith, make mee ſtrong in thee and in the power of thy might, ſeale me with the holy ſpirit of promiſe, as with the earneſt of my hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly inheritance, that ſo no anguiſh of ſickneſſe may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage me, no pang of death diſmay mee, no aſſault of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than ouercome mee; but that, come death when it will, or in what manner it ſhall pleaſe thee, I may boldly (through Chriſt) commit my ſoule to thee as vnto a faithful creator:
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:173418:88"/>
Grant me this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing for his ſake, who dyed to free me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death, &amp; from him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> had the power of death, euen for Chriſt Ieſus ſake. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="prayer">
               <head>
                  <hi>16. A Prayer more ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally</hi> fitted to the ſtate and occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of a ſicke perſon.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Moſt mercifull and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious God, thou, whoſe prouidence reacheth into the moſt withdrawne and ſolita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie places, and which cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt the beames of thy fauour to ſhine euen vpon chiefe ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, vouchſafe to caſt thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſionate ey vpon thine af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted creature, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou haſt laid vpon his bed of ſicknes.
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:173418:89"/>
Iuſt (O Lord) it is with thee thus to chaſten me: nay, if thou ſhouldeſt cruſh my body into many pieces, and ſuddenly plunge mee into hell, it were no more then my due deſert. What a ſtayned ſinner am I by nature, ſtript of al goodnes, and eaſie to be wrought vnto any, euen the vileſt euill? What a world of treſpaſſes haue béene ſince committed by mee, notwithſtanding the greatnes of thy patience, and the varietie of good meanes which thou haſt vſed both to informe and to guide me vnto godlineſſe? I will not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (O Lorde) I dare not, I cannot plead againſt thée; It
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:173418:89"/>
is my duety rather to magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie thy mercy, who art plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſo mildly &amp; ſo fatherly to correct me; it being free to thy iuſtice, to cut me off as an eare of Corne, and to giue mée o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to the prince of darkneſſe, &amp; to leaue me for euer to that woefull kingdome of eternall miſerie. Vnworthy I am (I moſt willingly confeſſe) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of my former ſlackenes and coldnes in this duety of calling vpon thy Name, to haue any ſmall acceſſe into thy preſence: Yet ſeeing thou art wont euer more to reſpect the trueth of thine owne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, then the deſert of thoſe which pray vnto thee, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:173418:90"/>
I beſeech thee, which art pleaſed to call thy ſelfe <hi>The hearer of Prayers;</hi> to hearken vnto the hearty and vnfained deſire of my ſoule. Sanctifie vnto mee (O Lord) this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſickneſſe, let it bee as thy ſchoole, in which I may truely learne to know my ſelfe more effectually then heretofore. Make me to conſider ſeriouſly that al paine and griefe is but the fruite of ſinne, and that as all ſickneſſe naturally makes way for death, ſo death (in it ſelf) is the fore-runner of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall condemnation. Bleſſe this thought and this medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſo vnto mee, that I may make it my firſt care (now in
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:173418:90"/>
this viſitation) to ſéeke peace and aſſurance of reconcile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with thy Maieſtie. To this ende giue mee a deepe touch and a ſenſible vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of my ſinnes by paſt, take from mee all guile of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, all diſpoſition to flatter or to ſooth vppe my ſelfe, or to leſſen eyther the number or qualitie of mine iniquities; Cauſe mee euen to breake and plough vppe my heart, to ſearch and to try my wayes, that ſo out of the abundance of my féeling, I may powre out a moſt plentifull and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere confeſſion before thee. Let mee remember it to bée
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:173418:91"/>
in vaine to ſéeke to hide that from thée, which thou (before whom all things are naked and open) doeſt know more fully and more directly then my ſelfe; and that the diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and laying open of my ſins, is the next way to finde thy mercy in forgiuing them.</p>
               <p>Adde withall that ſtrength vnto my ſcant and ſmoking fayth, that I may, amidde the ſight of mine owne tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, lay holde vpon the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite and fulnes of my Sauior. Make me hartily to diſclaime all hope of help by my ſelfe, or any other creature in Heauen or Earth whomſoeuer, and to caſt all my burthen vpon him,
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:173418:91"/>
who by himſelfe hath purged ſinne, and whoſe death is an abſolute and an alſufficient ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice for the guilt of all belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers. Oh that I may féele my ſelfe knit and vnited vnto him: ſo ſhall I, in and by him, be preſented blameles to thy Maieſtie. And becauſe (O Lord) I am full of imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and there is in my nature much weaknes, and a great deale of frowardnes and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines to repine and rebell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thy ordinance, therefore furniſh mee with neceſſary graces, &amp; with all ſuch giftes as thou knoweſt to be fitte for my preſent caſe: Endue mée with patience, to beare what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:173418:92"/>
it ſhall bee thy pleaſure to lay vpon me, and méekly to ſubmit my ſelfe to thy moſt wiſe appointments: Aſſure mee that thou which knoweſt whereof I am made, and that I am but duſt, wilt not op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe me with more then thou ſhalt giue me ſtrength &amp; pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to endure. Let mee not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire life, otherwiſe then for the further aduancement of thy glory. Subdue in me all loue &amp; liking of this preſent world, grant that the hope of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie which ſhalbe ſhewed here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, may be ſo ſtrong within me, that all things may ſeeme vile vnto mee in compariſon thereof. Make me comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:173418:92"/>
capable of the aduiſe and counſell of my Chriſtian friends, which in their loue ſhall goe about to refreſh my Soule. Make mee able alſo to ſpeake profitably and for good to thoſe that belong vnto mee; Put vpon mée and in mee charitable affections and thoughts, to, and concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning others, being ready to ſatiſfie where I haue fayled, and to remit euen where I haue receiued the greateſt wrong.</p>
               <p>Prepare mee to my laſt conflict, and ſtrengthen me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſathans aſſaults, that in deſpite of his malice, yet I may ſtill holde mee faſt
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:173418:93"/>
by thee, and reſolue, though thou ſlay me, yet to truſt vpon thee. And becauſe (ſuch is thy great goodneſſe to vs thy poore creatures) ſickeneſſe doth not alwayes exerciſe his full ſtrength vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our bodies: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore giue me (I beſéech thee) that wiſedome to make vſe of euery breathing, and of euery little time of eaſe which thou doeſt afforde mee, that in it I may gather ſtrength againſt the times of greater anguiſh. Bring ſtill into my minde, thoſe things which I haue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> time to time learned by thy word, that thereby I may bée quickned and find comfort in my greateſt neede. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:173418:93"/>
(O Lorde) as the time of departure ſhall approache, ſo let my ſoule draw neerer vnto thee, my heart powerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly crying, when ſickneſſe ſhall take away y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vſe of my tongue, <hi>Into thy hands I commend my Spirit: Come Lord Ieſu, come quickly.</hi> And when death hath parted my Soule from my body, let thy Angels (which do alwayes by thy ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment pitch their tents a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout thy ſeruants) conuey it into that place of reſt, which the blood of thy Sonne hath prouided and purchaſed for thy choſen. To which thy Sonne with thy ſelfe and thy bleſſed Spirit be prayſe and thankeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:173418:94"/>
now &amp; euermore. Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="prayer">
               <head>
                  <hi>17. A direction for thoſe</hi> who deſire to performe the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian duety of prayer on the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of a ſick friend or neighbor whom they come to viſite.</head>
               <p>WEe are vnworthy (O Lorde) to ſpeake vnto thy Maieſtie either for our ſelues or others: yet this duty lying vpon vs by commaund, &amp; hauing a promiſe of hearing annexed thereunto, wee are bold in Ieſus Chriſt to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend vnto thee the weake e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of this thy ſeruant. All ſicknes is from thee, &amp; to thee belong y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iſſues of death. Thou killeſt and y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> makeſt aliue thou bringeſt downe to the graue &amp;
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:173418:94"/>
thou rayſeſt vp; to whom ſhall we go in this and other our ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities, but onely vnto thee? Wee could wiſh (O gracious God) the continuance of his Chriſtian fellowſhip, the leng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thening and enlarging of his dayes, but wee willingly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect our wils to thy determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; Thou (Lord) knoweſt what is the beſt, &amp; therunto make vs (we beſéech thée) willingly and readily to ſubſcribe, &amp; to deſire both his life &amp; our own, onely ſo far forth as may be for his and our further good in the more dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; zealous aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cement of thy glory. Frame him alſo (we pray thee) vnto the like yéelding, and ſo bleſſe
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:173418:95"/>
vnto him this viſitation, that by it he may be more and more hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bled in the ſight of his owne ſinnes &amp; may encreaſe withall in an vnfayned and longing deſire after Chriſt: Enligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten his eyes, that hee may know what is the hope of his calling, &amp; what is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> excéeding greatnes of thy mercy and power towards all belieuers. Strengthen his faith, that hee may with it (vtterly renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing himſelfe) lay faſt holde vpon the merites of our onely Sauiour. Protect him againſt ſathan, blunt the edge of his aſſaults, that they may neuer wound him to deſpaire. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooue from him a dull ſpirit,
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:173418:95"/>
and all ſecure and hardned thoughts, all worldly deſires, al lingring after the deceiuing ſwéetneſſe of theſe earthly things. Giue him patience to beare, &amp; conſtancy to endure whatſoeuer it ſhalbe thy plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to inflict. Vouchſafe him comfort in conſcience, ioy in the ſpirit, peace in belieuing, together with a ſetled and wel grounded exſpectation of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life and ſaluation by thy Sonne. Graunt to vs tender and féeling hearts, that both his ſorrowes and the griefes of other of thy ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts may be apprehended, by vs as if they were our owne: Let thy word of grace bee in our lips, that
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:173418:96"/>
we may be able to ſpeak holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſoundly and chéerefully to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> comfort of his ſoule. Teach vs in him and in this houſe of mourning to ſée the ende of vs all, and to lay it to our hearts, that ſo wee may labour to bee prepared for our laſt depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. All theſe graces both for him and for our ſelues, we begge in all humilitie at thy mercifull hands, in the name and worthines of thy beloued Sonne, calling further on thee, as hee hath taught vs in his word; <hi>Our Father, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="prayer">
               <pb n="157" facs="tcp:173418:96"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>18. A thankeſgiuing for a</hi> ſicke man, if God be pleaſed to ſend recouery.</head>
               <p>SVffer me not (O Lord) to be in the number of thoſe, who are forward to aſke in the time of neede, but careleſſe to ſhew themſelues thankefull when mercy is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed. Make me as deſirous to come vnto thee with this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of prayſe, as I was ready to beg eaſe and refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the day of my great ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie. Thou haſt chaſtened me (O gratious God) and corrected me, but thou haſt not giuen mee ouer vnto death. I looked to haue beene cleane
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:173418:97"/>
depriued of the reſidue of my yeares and thought I ſhould haue ſéene man no more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the inhabitants of the world: but it was thy plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to deliuer my Soule from the pit of corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Oh what ſhal I render vnto thee for this and all other thy benefits to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards mee! Oh how and by what meanes ſhal I ſhew my ſelfe thankefull to thy Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie! I haue nothing (O Lord) to render thee but the calues of my lips; accept my ſeruice (I beſéech thée) in Ieſus Chriſt: and let not the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of this thy kindneſſe dye within me, but graunt that I may often recount thy mercy,
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:173418:97"/>
working there-with vpon mine owne heart, and apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it as an effectuall motiue to obedience. Make me euer mindfull of the vowes &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes which I made in my ſickneſſe, to ſerue thee more faithfully then heretofore, that I may make conſcience to performe them, knowing that thou delighteſt not in fooles; &amp; that by my neglect herein, I ſhall lay my ſelfe open vnto a greater iudgement. Teach me alſo to remember this, that albeit thou haſt now giuen me ſome little reſpite, yet I muſt not deceiue my ſelfe in putting far off the day of my death, but that I ought rather
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:173418:98"/>
to vſe my health &amp; ſtrength to the better fitting and more ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall preparing my ſelfe thereunto. Together with the encreaſe of bodily and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſtrength, encreaſe in me ſtrength of care to walk with thee, and to approoue my ſelfe vnto thee in al holy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and godlineſſe, being more zealous in Religion, more watchfull ouer my wayes, more earneſt in Prayer, more feruent in Spirit, more care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to profite by thy Word, more faithful in my place and calling then heretofore, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes looking for the bleſſed hope and appearing of Ieſus Chriſt my Sauiour: to whom
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:173418:98"/>
with thee &amp; the holy Ghoſt, let my heart féelingly &amp; effectually giue all honour, prayſe, might, maieſtie and dominion both now and for euer, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="prayer">
               <head>
                  <hi>19. A Prayer for a</hi> woman in the time of her trauaile.</head>
               <p>O Lord, I now finde by experience the trueth &amp; certaintie of thy word, &amp; the ſmart of that pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment which y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> laidſt vpon me being in the loynes of my Gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d-mother <hi>Eue,</hi> for my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce towards thee: Thou haſt greatly encreaſed the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owes of our ſex, &amp; our bearing of
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:173418:99"/>
children is ful of paine. Teach me by this, to ſée the deſert of ſinne, and to grow into the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which hath brought into the world ſuch ſtore of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie. Giue mee true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance &amp; pardon for my ſinnes paſt, that they may not ſtand at this time &amp; in this my néed, betwixt me &amp; thy mercy: Giue mee a comfortable féeling of thy loue in Chriſt, which may ſwéeten all other pangs, thogh neuer ſo violent or extreame: Make mee ſtill to lift vp my Soule vnto thee in my grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt anguiſh, knowing that thou alone muſt giue a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to the ordinarie meanes for my ſafe deliuery. Streng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:173418:99"/>
my weake body to the bearing of what ſorrow ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, by which it ſhall ſéeme good vnto thee to take triall of me. Make mee to remember, that howſoeuer it be with me, yet I am alwayes in thy ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, whoſe mercyes fayle not, and which canſt giue iſſue to the greateſt paine. And when thou haſt ſafely giuen mee the exſpected fruite of my wombe, make mee with a thankefull heart to conſecrate both it and the reſidue of my life to thy ſeruice, through Ieſus Chriſt my Sauiour and Redeemer. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="prayer">
               <pb n="164" facs="tcp:173418:100"/>
               <head>20. A Thankeſgiuing after <hi>deliuery.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BLeſſed bee thy great Name, (O my moſt deare &amp; louing Father) for thy large mercy to me moſt weake &amp; ſinfull wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. Thou haſt ſhewed thy power in my frailtie, and thy louing kindneſſe hath preuai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led againſt my vnworthineſſe. Thou mighteſt, for my ſinnes, haue left mee to periſh in my great extremitie: but thou haſt compaſſed me about with ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full deliuerance. Maruailous (O Lord) are thy workes, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite are thy mercyes, and my
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:173418:100"/>
Soule by preſent experience knoweth it well. O my Soule, prayſe thou the Lord, and all that is within mee praiſe his holy Name. My Soule, prayſe thou the Lorde and forget not all his benefits: hee hath heard thy Prayers, hee hath looked vpon thy ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe, hee hath forgiuen thine iniquities, he hath healed thine infirmities, hee hath redéemed thy life from the graue, hée hath euen crowned thée with compaſſions. Oh giue mee (I beſéech thee) a thankefull heart, not only now, while the memorie &amp; ſenſe of thy fauor is freſh before me, but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g as I haue my being
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:173418:101"/>
Graunt that I may learne by this euidence of thy mercy and might, for euer hereafter to depend vpon thee: Quicken me vp to all holy dutyes, that my thankefulneſſe may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in my pure and Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an cariage. Make me a kinde and carefull Mother, willing to vnder-goe the paines and troubles of education: let no niceneſſe or curioſitie hinder me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe ſeruices to which both Nature &amp; Religion haue appointed mee. Let mee alſo bee carefull heereafter, when time ſhall require, to ſeaſon that which thou haſt giuen mee, with the knowledge of thee, and of thy Sonne; that
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:173418:101"/>
my deſire may manifeſtly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to bee ſet for the encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of thy kingdom. Vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe ſo to order my affections, &amp; to bring them into obedience vnder thee, that if it ſhould bée thy pleaſure either now or hereafter to take this infant from mee, I may patiently ſubmit my ſelf to thy appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And now (O good God) perfite in mee that ſtrength which y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt begun, make me to growe in care to ſerue thée faithfully both in the duetyes of piety, &amp; in other buſineſſes of my place and calling; that I may be a comfort to my huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, an example to my neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, a grace to my profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:173418:102"/>
&amp; a means of glory to thy Name, through Ieſus Chriſt my Lord and Sauiour. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="prayer">
               <head>
                  <hi>21. A Prayer for thoſe which</hi> are employed in the aſſiſtance &amp; helpe of a trauailing woman.</head>
               <p>IT is not our diligence (O Lord) or paines which can do any thing without thy bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, &amp; our ſins are ſufficient to bring thy curſe vpon whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer we vndertake. Be pleaſed (we pray thée) to be reconciled to vs in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blood of thy Sonne: Make vs to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we are here in thy preſence, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all our thoughts, words &amp; actions are open to thy ſight: proſper y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſines for which wee are come
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:173418:102"/>
together: put far fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs all ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſticious co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceits, &amp; idle fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, &amp; teach vs to ſéek help on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy grace. Enable vs to ſpeak comfortably to this pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned woman, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we may further her dependance vpon thy holy Maieſtie, and may be a means vnder thee of her true refre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing in her ſharpeſt fits. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh vs with ſkill, and her with ſtrength, patiently to awaite y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> appointed time of her deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance: &amp; knit al our hearts vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, that we may feare thy Name, noting &amp; obſeruing thy mercy and power in all thy works, &amp; ſtudying to giue thee prayſe and glory for the ſame, through Ieſus Chriſt our on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Lord &amp; Sauiour. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="prayer">
               <pb n="170" facs="tcp:173418:103"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>22. A Thankeſgiuing</hi> after, when God hath bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed their paines in the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans deliuerie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lorde, wee haue ſéene thy goodnes, and haue receiued an apparant token of thy readines to heare the Prayers of thoſe which call vpon thée, and to ſuccour thoſe which flye vnto thee for thy helpe. Thou haſt giuen eaſe and deliuerance to the woman, light and life to the infant, ioy and gladneſſe to vs all. The glory and prayſe is thine alone; Fill our hearts
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:173418:103"/>
with thankefulneſſe, &amp; make vs forward both now &amp; here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after to prouoke and ſtirre vp one another thereunto. And And let not our thankefulnes ſtand in words onely or out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſhewes, but cauſe it to appeare in our whole courſe; that the obedience, the ſobrie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, the modeſtie, the vertue of our liues may witnes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full féeling of our hearts. Goe on in thy mercy, (wee pray thee) both to the Mother and her babe, continue &amp; encreaſe their ſtrength, ſo as may ſerue beſt for thy glory. And as thou haſt added one vnto the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of mankind, ſhewing thy wonderful wiſedome &amp; power
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:173418:104"/>
both in the framing of him in the wombe, &amp; in bringing him foorth into this light: ſo in thy time adde him alſo to thy Church, and beget him again vnto a liuely hope, by the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall ſéed of thy holy word, deliuering him from the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of darkeneſſe, (in which by nature we are al) into the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious libertie of thy choſen. And if it ſhall ſo ſéeme good to thee, to lay any further triall eyther of ſickenes or death vpon this thy ſeruant, or vpon the fruite of her wombe, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare vs all to a patient and quiet bearing of thy hand, and to a contented &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting vpon thy gracious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence,
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:173418:104"/>
aſſuring our ſelues, that all things ſhall turne to the good and benefit of thy cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen. Heare vs (O Lord) and accept vs, and forgiuing the weakenes of our Prayers, graunt vs all néedfull graces out of the rich ſtore-houſe of thy bottomleſſe bounty, and that for Ieſus Chriſt our gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Redéemer. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="prayer">
               <head>
                  <hi>23. A Prayer for a</hi> Souldier, fighting for his Countrey, or the confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates thereof.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lord, it is thy glorie to bee called <hi>(The Lord of
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:173418:105"/>
hoſtes)</hi> and it is thou alone, from whom, when men haue made their moſt politicke and puiſſant preparations, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie muſt be looked for. Drawe my heart, I beſéech thee, from all relying vpon my own va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor, or vpon the ſtrength of the battaile in which I ſtand; and teach me to looke vpward, and to waite and truſt onely vpon thee. Thou giueſt conqueſt, and thou giueſt courage; thou deliuereſt from the perill of the ſword, or elſe makeſt death a meanes of happineſſe to thy ſeruants. Forgiue my ſinnes, I pray thee, and aſſure mee of pardon by the witneſſe of thy ſpirit, that the guilt thereof
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:173418:105"/>
make not my heart to tremble in me, and to behold death as a meſſenger to conuey me in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hell. If thou (O Lord) bée on my ſide, peace being made betwixt thée and my Soule through Chriſt, what can bee againſt mee, what hazard can befall my Soule! Nothing ſhall be able to depriue mee of thy loue. Let not ſpoyle, or blood, or mine owne aduance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be the ends of mine at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, but make me to ayme onely at thy glory in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of thy trueth, and in the good and ſafety of the State wherein I liue. The iſſue of all things to thee (O Lorde) is knowen, but to man it is
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:173418:106"/>
hidden, prepare me therefore indifferently to whatſoeuer ſhall befall me. If I dye, giue mee comfort in my laſt brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and take my Soule into thy gracious hands: If I bee taken captiue, giue mee pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, giue mee wiſedome and godly courage to doe nothing contrary to the honour of my countrey, or preiudiciall to the profeſſion of a faithful Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. If I returne with life and victorie, make me thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; kéepe mee from taking fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee any part of thy glory. Preſerue mee from thoſe rio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, laſciuious and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming courſes, which are the vſuall fruits of good ſucceſſe;
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:173418:106"/>
Let me not thinke deuotion to be an enemie to reſolution, or that a religious feare of thy Maieſtie doeth abate the ſpirit that ſhould bee in a Souldier: but ſettle me in this, that the aſſurance of a lawfull cauſe, the hope and confidence of a better life by the merites of Chriſt, the care to pleaſe thee and to depend vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy power, are the onely true grounds of valour, which can giue a man boldneſſe and life in the day of battaile. Vouchſafe me theſe and all other needfull fauours in and for Chriſt Ieſus ſake. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="prayer">
               <pb n="178" facs="tcp:173418:107"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>24. A Prayer for a</hi> man trauailing by Sea, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout his lawfull buſineſſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Heauenly Father, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whoſe eares the Prayers of humbled ſinners haue fréedome of acceſſe out of euery place: let it pleaſe thee, to encline to me, who being prouoked by mine owne preſent néede, and taking heart vnto my ſelfe by thy liberall &amp; large promiſes, doe deſire to powre out my Soule before thy Maieſtie: Heere (O Lord) by reaſon of the calling and place, in which it hath béene thy prouidence to
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:173418:107"/>
ranke mee, I am come downe to the ſea in a Ship, and I doe now ſée thy workes, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually beholde thy wonders in this déepe. How eaſie a thing is it vnto thee, when thou rayſeſt a ſtorme, &amp; lifteſt vp the waues, not only to toſſe vs to and fro, and to make vs ſtagger like a drunken man, but vtterly to ſwallow vs vp, and to turne vpon our heads in a moment the bottome of theſe mouing houſes in which wee are! It is thy great and excéeding mercy, that theſe ſwelling billowes &amp; foaming ſurges doe not drinke vs in, and ſo make our bodyes to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as a prey, eyther to that
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:173418:108"/>
great <hi>Leuiathan</hi> (the Whale) whom thou haſt made to play here, or to ſome other of thy creatures, with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ire varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and troupes whereof this vaſt body is repleniſhed. But it is euen thou (O mightie Lord) which layedſt the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of the earth, &amp; which diddeſt ſhut vp the Sea with doores: thou didſt firſt gather theſe waters together as vpon an heape, and ſtoredſt vp the depths in thy treaſures: thogh the waues are maruailous, though the floods lift vp their voyce: though y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> waters rage and be troubled, and the very mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taines ſhake at the ſurges of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, yet thou art much
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:173418:108"/>
more mightie, thou ſoone ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſeſt the noiſe, and turneſt the ſtorme into a calme.</p>
               <p>Look gratiouſly therfore vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on mee, I beſéech thée, teach mée to vnderſtand the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of thy terror, by that fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes of thy creatures which I do ſtill behold: Cauſe me to reſt my hope and comfort vpon the power of thy mercie, let that be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> anchor of my Soule both ſure and ſtedfaſt. And leſt my ſins not being pardoned, ſhould be a hinderance &amp; ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>page to thy fauor, I pray thee, ſettle in mee an hearty &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fained deteſtation of them, a godly griefe and ſorrow for them, a ſtedfaſt reſolution and
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:173418:109"/>
purpoſe in the whole courſe of my life to ſtriue againſt them. Open my heart, that I may often &amp; earneſtly ſue and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate for thy grace in thy ſon, and may neuer giue ouer till I féele in my conſcience ſome comfortable aſſurance that thou haſt forgiuen me. Fit &amp; prepare me to thine owne ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointments; If it be thy plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure that I ſhould heere ende my dayes, I know well, that the ſoule which thou kéepeſt cannot miſcary: To thee ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend my ſpirit, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake mee not (I pray thee) in my laſt breathing. Albeit theſe waues may ouerwhelme my body, yet let them not bee able
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:173418:109"/>
to quench my comfort, or to plunge mee downe into deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire. Graunt me euer to lay faſt hold vpon my Sauiour, that neither ſea, death, nor hell may ſeparate mee from his grace. And if it ſhal ſéeme good vnto thee, to bring me ſafe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that hauen where I would be; Oh that I may neuer for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get thy kindneſſe, but may make conſcience to performe that obedience which I am now ready to vowe in my ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie. Make me alwayes to take as great delight to ſerue thée, as I am now forward to aſke, and deſirous to receiue life and ſafety from thée. Heare me (O Lord) in theſe and other
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:173418:110"/>
my petitions, forgiuing my vnworthineſſe in the merites of Ieſus Chriſt thy bleſſed Sonne, and my great Redée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="prayer">
               <head>
                  <hi>25. A Prayer applyed to the</hi> ſtate and condition of a malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, condemned by law to dy, and drawing neere to the time of his execution.</head>
               <p>VOuchſafe, (O thou God of all mercie and compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion) to looke with pity vpon the moſt wofull caſe of a poore wretch, ready by the ſword of Iuſtice to bee cut off, as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy to liue amongſt men; &amp; like alſo without thy ſpéedy fauor to be ſhut out of heauen,
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:173418:110"/>
and to haue my part in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond death; Trueth it is (O Lorde) that all this, though it bée grieuous, yet is no more then my deſert: and touching that bodily death, whereto I am adiudged, I muſt confeſſe it to bee thy mercie and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe toward me, that I haue béene found out by the eye of the Maigſtrate, and ſtopped by the power of authoritie from going on into further e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill. I beſéech thée, that my death may bee both a chaſtize<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to mee, and an aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizement to others, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine themſelues within the liſtes of ciuill obedience.</p>
               <p>But concerning my Soule,
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:173418:111"/>
which is now ere long to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare before the Tribunall ſeate of thy great Maieſtie , I humbly pray thee, to be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull thereunto. I cannot but acknowledge, that if thou giue me my due reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>penſe, I muſt néeds be thruſt into that dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full place of infinite &amp; eternall torment, which thou haſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for the wicked, the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning whereof is fire and much wood, and which thy breath like a riuer of brimſtone doth kindle: neither ſée I in my ſelf, or in any creature, any means or poſſibilitie to eſcape. Feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto mee hath beene the face of an earthly Iudge, &amp; the ſentence of death to bee inflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:173418:111"/>
vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this my houſe of clay, hath made my heart to quake within mee; What then will become of mee, when I ſhall be arraigned before thee, at whoſe rebuking the very fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of the earth are diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, &amp; before whom no man liuing can be iuſtified? Thou (O Lorde) knoweſt all mine iniquities, they are ſealed vp with thee, as in a hugge, they are all noted in thy regiſters: Although I haue many times ſought for the couering of my euill wayes to hide my ſelfe in the darkeneſſe of the night, ſuppoſing that no eye ſhould ſée me, yet thou haſt ſtill com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed my pathes, and beene
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:173418:112"/>
accuſtomed to all my wayes, there hath not bin a thought in my heart or a worde in my tongue but thou haſt wholly knowen it: Often haue I ſaid in my heart, God will not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, he hath forgotten, hee hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth away his face &amp; wil neuer ſée, I ſhal neuer be mooued nor be in danger: Thy word I had no delight to heare, I hated knowledge, I would none of thy cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel, I ſought to damme vp the mouth of my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it might not check me; when my friends admoniſhed me, I hated &amp; ſcorned their reproofe: Thus it was a paſtime to mée to doe naughtily, wickedneſſe was ſwéete in my mouth, I
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:173418:112"/>
fauoured it, and would not be perſwaded to forſake it: Iuſtly therefore (O Lord) haſt thou thus ouertaken me, and made me to eat the fruit of my owne way, bringing me to be a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacle to the world, to dye as one of the fooles of the people; Yet (O gratious God) ſith there is mercy with thee, and that thou art very ready to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue, be fauourable, I entreat thee, to mee a moſt vnworthy ſinner. <hi>Manaſſe</hi> being put in fetters, and bound in chaines, prayed vnto thee, and humbled himſelfe greatly before thee in his tribulation, &amp; thou waſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated of him: The woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Canaan,</hi> whom thou tearmedſt to be no better then a dog, yet thou diddeſt afforde her ſome crummes of thy mercy,
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:173418:113"/>
and didſt cauſe it to bee vnto her as ſhe deſired. The thiefe, at his execution, confeſſed his ſinne, &amp; prayed to bee remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred in thy kingdome, &amp; thou didſt promiſe him an entrance into Paradiſe. O Lord, are not theſe things written for my learning, that I through the comfort of theſe examples might haue hope? Hath thy Word ſpoken it in vaine, that at what time ſoeuer a ſinner ſigheth vnto thée, thou wilt put all his wickedneſſe from before thée? Shall I thinke that thou wilt call mee being laden with my ſinnes, to come vnto thee, and then when I come wilt not accept mee?
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:173418:113"/>
Make me (I pray thee) to ſée the depth of my ſinnes, that I may not beguile my Soule, by leſſening eyther the weight or number of mine iniquities: Worke me to a true and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſembled acknowledgement and confeſſion of them, euen before others, that they which ſée my end and know mine e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, may haue ſome euidence of my repentance, and may learne by me to beware of the deceitfulneſſe of ſinne. Ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble me to looke with the eye of my faith vpon my crucified Sauior, caſting my ſelf whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vpon him and deſiring by him to bee hidden from thy wrath. Giue mee ſome taſte
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:173418:114"/>
of thy loue, and ſome inward and ſecret pledge of thy being reconciled to mee for his ſake. Strengthen mee againſt the feare of death, that albeit I haue euery way iuſt cauſe to tremble at it, it being both the deſert of my offence to men, &amp; the wages of my ſinne againſt thee; yet hauing ſome aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in my Soule, that the ſting thereof is plucked out, I may embrace it in my boſome, and entertaine it as an end ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for my miſerie, &amp; as a meanes to bring me vnto hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines. Thus (O Lord) with fulneſſe of deſire (out of the bottome of this miſery and ſhame which I am fallen into)
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:173418:114"/>
to fly vnto thy mercy, and to be ſhrouded vnder the ſhadow of thy grace, I commend my ſelfe, my ſoule and my body into thy hands, praying thée not to caſt off him, which hath no hope but onely in thée, and that alone in and by Ieſus Chriſt my only Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="prayer">
               <head>
                  <hi>26. A Prayer riſing out of</hi> the ſerious meditation of the laſt Iudgement.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lord, thou haſt reuealed it in thy holy Word, that the faſhion and figure of this world muſt paſſe away, &amp; that as by appointment wee muſt all dye, ſo alſo wée muſt all
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:173418:115"/>
appeare before the iudgement ſeate of Chriſt, and that from thence ſome ſhal go into euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting paine, and ſome into life eternall. This, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Atheiſts and Epicures and Libertines of the world doe thinke to bee but a méere fable, they ſay in their hearts; <hi>The Lord will doe neither good nor euill.</hi> But yet (O Lord) as thou haſt deliuerd this in thy Word, (of which one iote nor tittle ſhall not periſh) ſo thou haſt not left it without a ſufficient proofe in the very boſome of euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: The accuſing or excuſing of our owne thoughts, the ſecret checks accompanying thoſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils to which none is priuy,
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:173418:115"/>
the feares of wicked men, who are continually as one that trauaileth of child, flying oft times when none purſueth them, and being chaſed at the very ſhaking of a leafe, are an euident proofe of thy proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and a certaine aſſura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce written as with a point of a Diamond (which can neuer be done out) that verely there is fruite for the righteous, and doubtles there is a God that iudgeth the earth. This truth (O Lord my God) thou haſt taught mee to belieue, and I make no doubt, but it ſhall ſhortly come to paſſe. It was ſayd long ſince that the Iudge did ſtand before the doore, and
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:173418:116"/>
that hee which ſhould come, would come &amp; would not tary; and now, the height of iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is ſuch, and ſinne is grown to that perfection, that it cannot ſtand with thy Iuſtice much longer to forbeare. Teach me (I pray thee) as I doe know &amp; belieue this, ſo to make a true &amp; profitable vſe of my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. Let it bee euer in my thoughts, and in my beſt and moſt ſerious meditations: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I am about by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> proue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of my corrupted nature to doe euill, let the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance hereof be a bridle to me to reſtrayne me: when I am like by the iniquitie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> times to ſuffer euill among men,
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:173418:116"/>
let the exſpectation of the right which thou wilt then do to the oppreſſed, be a comfort to mee to refreſh me. Eſpecially (O Lord) grant mee to keep daily (as it were) a priuy ſeſſions in the cloſet of mine owne heart, arraigning my ſelfe before thy iudgement ſeat, ſearching and trying my wayes, accuſing my ſelfe before thee, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whom nothing can be hid, confeſſing my vnworthineſſe, bewailing my corruptions, ſuing with al inſtant earneſtneſſe for thy grace &amp; fauour in thy Son. O that I may learn thus to iudge my ſelfe, that I may not be iudged of thee in that day.</p>
               <p>Suffer me not to flatter my
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:173418:117"/>
ſelfe or to bleſſe my Soule in any euill way, or to goe about to finde hidings and couerts for my ſinnes; inaſmuch as all things are naked in thy ſight, and that in that great terrible day thou wilt lighten the things which are hid in darkeneſſe, and make mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt the counſell of all mens hearts. Let mee not imagine this thy great ſeſſion to be like the courſes among men, in which oft times by vniuſt meanes the vileſt offenders do procure eſcapes: but make me to know, as the trueth is, that with thée there is no hope by corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or fauour, or fraud, or importunitie of ſute, to find
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:173418:117"/>
euaſions. Thou art the Iudge of all the world, and thou wilt doe right; euery man ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the things which haue beene done in his body, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that he hath done, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it bée good or euill. And whereas (O Lord) it is a great griefe to thy ſeruants, to liue among the vngodly, it muſt néedes vexe their righteous ſoules to heare and ſée their vnlawfull deeds, let this be my comfort, that though it be thy pleaſure to ſuffer with long patience the veſſels of wrath, &amp; to permit the tares to growe vppe with the Wheate vntill the harueſt, yet then thy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels ſhall come, and ſhall ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:173418:118"/>
out of thy Church all things that offend, and bring the iuſt into the kingdome of their father. Seeing alſo (O gratious God) that whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer in this world wil liue god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſhall ſuffer, and ly open to the wrongs and iniuries and reproches of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked; Grant that if at any time, eyther my name be put out as euill, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe my eſtate or profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or life, for thy trueths ſake be called into queſtion, I may poſſeſſe my Soule with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, looking for the bleſſed hope and appearing of thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, knowing that then the iuſt, what diſgraces ſo-euer are now caſt vpon them, ſhall
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:173418:118"/>
ſhine as the light in thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. Finally (O Lord) make make me daily to grow ſo wearie of this vaine &amp; wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched world, and of the heauy load of mine owne corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and of this body of death which is vpon mee, &amp; to ſtriue to gather that aſſurance of an intereſt in that glory which ſhall be ſhewed hereafter, that I may looke for this great day and in my deſires may ſigh for it and haſten to it; and that whenſoeuer it commeth, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d waking with my la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p of oyle in my hand, may haue cauſe to lift vp my head, not doubting but to haue a graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous admittance into my ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ioy.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="202" facs="tcp:173418:119"/>Graunt mee this for his ſake, which ſitteth at thy right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, to make requeſt for mee, Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt the Mediatour of thy choſen. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="prayer">
               <head>
                  <hi>27. A Prayer fitted</hi> to the time of warre.</head>
               <p>O Almightie God, who art hie aboue all nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and whoſe glory is aboue the heauens, the comfortable ſucceſſe of all enterpriſes is from thée onely to bee looked for; Thou art hee which giueſt victorie vnto kings, to thee it is all one to ſaue by many or by fewe, thou
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:173418:119"/>
canſt make one to chaſe a thouſand, thou canſt cauſe the hearts euen of the moſt vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant to melt, their hands to bée weake, their mindes to faint, and their knees to fall away like water. If thou fight for vs, wee cannot miſcary: if thou fauour vs not, wee muſt néeds bee diſcomfited. O bée gracious vnto vs, and bee on our ſide, now that men are ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen vp againſt vs. They take craftie counſell againſt thy Church, and conſult how to cut vs off from being a nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and by what meanes to quench the light of thy truth, which ſhineth in our ſtreetes. Their deſire is to embrue their
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:173418:120"/>
hands in our blood, and to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance their owne ambition by our ouerthrow. O turne their counſels into fooliſhnes, let not their miſchieuous imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons proſper, leſt they bee too proud: O our God, make them like vnto a whéel, &amp; as the ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wind, ſcatter y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that delight in war. Go out (O Lorde) with our armies, giue wiſedom and courage to our captaines, gird them with ſtrength vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> battel, be with our Souldiers, teaching their hands to war, &amp; their fingers to fight: Aſſiſt al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> conſultations, proſper y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> policies, crown thoſe enterpriſes with good ſucceſſe which are vndertaken for the
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:173418:120"/>
common good &amp; comfort of the State. Doubtleſſe (O Lord) we haue deſerued thine anger, &amp; our ſins do cry loud in thine eares for vengeance: and it were but iuſt with thee, if thou ſhouldeſt make vs a prey and ſpoyle vnto our enemies; But (O gracious God) let vs fall now into thy hands, (for thy mercies are great) &amp; let vs not fal into the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of men, whoſe diſpleaſure at vs is not for our ſins, but for our profeſſion and religions ſake, and that they may fill their own enlarged &amp; vnſatiable deſires with thoſe bleſſings of wealth which thou haſt giuen vs: Put therefore thy hooke into their noſtrils, &amp; bring them backe by the ſame way they came. Let it appear y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <pb n="206" facs="tcp:173418:121"/>
thou art in the middes of vs, &amp; that wee ſhall not bée mooued, that thou wilt help vs and that very early: Let there be none inuaſion, nor going out, nor no crying in our ſtréets; But ſet thou peace in our borders, make ſtrong the barres of our gates, eſpecially let the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel of thy Sonne ſound yet louder amongſt vs, that by it many Soules may bee gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto thée. So we thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple &amp; the ſhéepe of thy paſture ſhall prayſe thee for euer, and from generation to generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on we will ſet foorth thy glory, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord and onely Sauiour. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="prayer">
               <pb n="207" facs="tcp:173418:121"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>28. Another of like</hi> nature, reſpecting the time of Dearth and Famine.</head>
               <p>CLeanneſſe of teeth (O Lord) and ſcarceneſſe of bread, haue béene aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently threatened by thee, as iudgements vpon the ſonnes of men for their ſinnes. Many wayes alſo thou haſt to turne a fruit-full land into barrenneſſe for the wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the Inhabitants: Thou canſt make the Heauen ouer our head as braſſe, &amp; the earth vnder vs as yron, by bringing a drought vpon the land. Or elſe thou canſt cauſe the ſéed to
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:173418:122"/>
rotte vnder the clods, by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bottels of heauen to powre out raine in too great abu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dance: or when the Corne is come vp, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> art able to ſmite it with blaſting &amp; mildeaw, or to ſend among vs thy great hoſte, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> graſhopper, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> canker, the caterpiller and the palmer worme, ſo that although much bee ſowen, yet little ſhall bee brought into the barne. Or if the Corne doe grow ripe vnto the harueſt, it is in thy power ſuddainly to ſend in an enemy, to eat the fruit of the land, and to deuoure the labour of the people. And though the bread do come to be ſet in plenty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs, yet thy hand is not
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:173418:122"/>
ſhortened, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> canſt take away y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtaffe thereof, ſo that wee ſhall eat &amp; not be ſatiſfied. Thus (O Lord) y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt euen ſtore-houſes of puniſhments, ſo that our hearts can not endure, nor our hands be ſtrong in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalt haue to doe with vs. And heereof we haue now already ſome experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce; For now thou haſt in part begun to puniſh our abuſe of thy creatures, our fulnes of bread, our conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt of the ſpiritual food of our ſoules, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> outward ſcarcity: The time is com, by gréedy worldlings long exſpected, in which they may make the meaſure ſmall and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prices great, ſelling euen the very refuſe of the Wheat;
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:173418:123"/>
Their treading is vpon the poore, their deſire is to ſwallow vp the néedy of the land. Look mercifully (O Lord) vpon vs, wée beſéech thée: lift vp thine hand, forget not the poor. Thou prepareſt for the rauen his meate when his birds cry to thee, wandring for lack of food, thou takeſt no delight in the confuſion of thy creatures: thou haſt promiſed, that if wée ſéeke to thée, we ſhall want no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that is good, thou wilt preſerue vs in the time of dearth, and in the dayes of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine wee ſhall haue inough. Accompliſh (wée beſéech thée) theſe thy gracious promiſes; Saue vs from this encreaſing
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:173418:123"/>
miſerie, and deliuer vs from their crueltie, which being without all bowels of mercy, doe reſpect nothing but their owne commoditie. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe (O Lord) our ſinnes doe ſeparate betwixt thee and vs, and doe hinder good things from vs: therefore humble our ſoules vnder thy mighty hand, make vs to ſee and to conſider our owne deſeruings, drawe from vs an hearty and ſincere acknowledgement, how great cauſe wee haue giuen thee to affamiſh both our bodies and ſoules for euer. Giue vs an vnderſtanding of our particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar groſſe ſinnes which doe lay vs open to this iudgement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:173418:124"/>
others: namely our wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neſſe, our pride, our luxuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, our riot, our feaſtings without feare, our want of mercy to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore, our ſpurning with the héele againſt thee, our forgetting thee in the dayes of our plenty, but chiefly our loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of that ſpirituall Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah, that heauenly diet of thy ſacred Word, prouided in thy abundant mercy for our Soules.</p>
               <p>O make vs aſhamed for theſe and other our monſtrous ſins, beſides thoſe perſonall euils wherewith we are each of vs iuſtly to be charged. Beget in vs a care to renounce and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake our ſinnes, equall to our
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:173418:124"/>
deſire for the putting away of thy iudgements. Forgiue vs in Ieſus Chriſt, and vouchſafe vs (as a pledge of thy loue) ſtrength and grace to walke in a greater meaſure of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence then heretofore. And now (O Lord) teach vs to rely vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thy prouiding, and to know that when all things faile, yet thy mercies are the ſame, and thy power to help is not dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed. Thou canſt ſuddenly by meanes to ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnknowen, turne the greateſt penury in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to plenty, thou canſt make a little to ſtretch farre, and canſt proportion our appetites to our ſtore.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="214" facs="tcp:173418:125"/>O make vs to depend on thee, and to ſtudy more how to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite by thy hand, then to haue thy rod remooued from vs. And when thou ſhalt ſhew thy ſelfe to haue heard our Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, by ſending greater plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, let vs not forget our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent want, but graunt that we may labour to bee thankefull, and endeauour after a more ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber vſe of thy bleſſings then heretofore. Heare vs in this, and in all other our requeſts, for Chriſtes ſake, and for thine owne promiſe ſake. Amen. <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="prayer">
               <pb n="215" facs="tcp:173418:125"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>29. Another like,</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to the time of ſome great contagion.</head>
               <p>WHither ſhall wee goe (O Lorde) in the day of our affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, but onely vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee! Thou alone canſt ſaue, and out of thy hands none is able to giue deliuera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy at this time is thy hand vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs, and fearefull is the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe with which thou haſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted vs: Wee are afrayde one friend and neighbour of another, and nothing is before vs but preſent death: Scarſely can we looke foorth, but we ſée
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:173418:126"/>
ſome one or other amongſt vs caried away to the graue, &amp; the mourners going about the ſtreets.</p>
               <p>Wée muſt needes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that though this he grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous, yet it is the ſmalleſt part of our deſert; It is iuſt with thee, to ſmite vs with botches and ſcabs that cannot bee hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and to make the peſtilence euen to cleaue vnto our loines and to ſwéep vs away from off the earth, euen as a man ſwée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth away doung till all bee gone. For, how haue we mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied our iniquities before thee, and to what a ſhameleſſe and intolerable meaſure are our ſinnes encreaſed? Many
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:173418:126"/>
warnings haue béene giuen by thy Miniſters, thou haſt ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen early and late, and ſent vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs by them; yet wee haue made our hearts as an Ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant ſtone, and haue put farre from vs the euill day, perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding our ſelues that their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons were but wind, and that they did but commend vnto vs their own fancies; Thus haue we encouraged our ſelues in euill, and haue ſet thy iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments at nought, euery one turning to his owne courſe, as the horſe ruſheth to the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell, adding drunkenneſſe to thirſt, and falling away from thee more and more. But (O Lorde) giue vs now at the
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:173418:127"/>
laſt remorſefull and repentant hearts, make vs (as it were) to ſmite vpon our thigh as a ſigne that wee ſee our wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drings, and that we are aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of our ſinnes: Embolden vs in the name of Chriſt to come into thy preſence, and in all earneſtneſſe of ſpirit to cry vnto thee, <hi>Take away our iniquities and receiue vs gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly.</hi> Teach vs as well to feare ſinne, the cauſe of this waſting ſickeneſſe, as we doe the ſickneſſe it ſelfe, which is the fruite of ſinne. Comfort vs, according to the dayes that thou haſt afflicted vs, and let the ſwéet feeling of the graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous teſtimony of thy Spirit,
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:173418:127"/>
ſpeaking peace vnto our ſoules, preuaile againſt all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſadnes, or cauſe of griefe, or ſorrow whatſoeuer. Say (O Lord) vnto thy deſtroying Angel, <hi>It is ſufficient; holde thy hand:</hi> Or if it be thy plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to ſtretch thine hand yet further, and to take vs away alſo, O prepare vs to thine owne purpoſe, endue vs with a holy patience to endure the vtmoſt triall: and graunt that whatſoeuer befall our earthly tabernacles, yet our ſoules may bee alwayes acceptable vnto thee, and al for Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ſake, who hath loued vs, &amp; giuen himſelfe to be a ſacrifice of a ſwéet ſmelling ſauor vnto thee. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="prayer">
               <pb n="220" facs="tcp:173418:128"/>
               <head>30. A Meditation or Prayer <hi>neceſſary for a poore man.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TRueth it is (O Lorde) that to my mutinous &amp; repining nature, want is of all things moſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſtful, and pouertie is a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den euen intolerable. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times I am ready to call thy iuſtice in queſtion, who mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſureſt out ſo large &amp; ouerflow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a portion vnto ſome, and yet art ſo ſtrait and ſparing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards mee. Sometimes &amp; do almoſt condemne Religion to be méerely vanity, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> louers whereof lye open to ſo great extremitie; Otherwhiles, my
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:173418:128"/>
owne heart chargeth me with hypocriſie, telling me that no man euer periſhed being an innocent, and that if I did ſo feare thee as I ſhould, thou couldeſt not thus forſake mee. And much adoe haue I to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter my owne affections, and to reſtraine my ſelfe from put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting foorth my hand to wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and from taking ſome ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge courſe for my own ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply. Thus (O Lorde) I am ſtraitened, thus I am euen haunted with whole troupes of vnquiet thoughtes: all which, by the continuance and enlargement of my owne ſcarcitie, and by the vncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionateneſſe which I finde
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:173418:129"/>
among the men of this yron age, are rather multiplyed and encreaſed in mee, then any way ſlaked or diminiſhed. But eternally bleſſed bee thy great Name, which haſt ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the gates of thy mercy, &amp; giuen hope of hearing and of help, to the baſeſt and pooreſt amongſt men. Thou accepteſt not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perſons, no not of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, thou regardeſt not the rich ſooner then the poore. Behold therefore (O louing Father in Ieſus Chriſt) to thee doe I cry, to thy Mercy-ſeat doe I ſtretch out my féeble hands. I haue learned (O Lorde) that miſerie commeth not foorth of the duſt, neither doeth affliction
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:173418:129"/>
ſpring out of the earth; the pillars of the world are thine, thou openeſt or ſhutteſt thy hand at thine owne pleaſure. Thy wiſedom alſo is infinite, and thy iudgements are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearcheable: who ſhall pleade with thee, to aſke thee a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of thy wayes? Let it bee inough for mee, that it is thy pleaſure thus to debaſe mee; Am I not in thy hand as the clay in the potters? If thou doe giue me a larger portion, it is thy bounty: if thou doe abridge me, what haue I to complain, or what challenge can I make to that, which thou keepeſt from mée? Teach mee (I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſéech thee) not to look ſo much
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:173418:130"/>
vpon this, what others haue, as to conſider well, how little I for my part doe deſerue to haue. If I doe but breath vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the face of the earth, if I had no houſe but the open ayre, no garments but ragges, no food, but the bread and the water of affliction, or the crummes that fal from ſome rich mans table, it were infinitely more then then my beſt deſert. A ſinfull and vnthankefull wretch, as I haue alwayes béene, what can I ſay is due vnto mee but perpetuall ſhame? When I iudge rightly of all things, ſo farre am I from being able to ſay that thou haſt wronged me, or dealt too ſtraightly with
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:173418:130"/>
mee, that I muſt rather ſtirre vp my ſelfe to magnifie thy mercie which haſt not layde vpon mee the vtmoſt of thy wrath, but haſt giuen mee a time and an opportunity to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent. Let theſe things (I pray thée) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoueraintie of thy pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, the depth of thy wiſedome, the foulenes of mine owne deſert, the kindneſſe which (notwithſtanding ſome out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward hardſhippe) thou haſt vouchſafed to my ſoule, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate my violent affections, curbe my raging and diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented thoughts, bring my ranging paſſions into order, that I may alwayes ſay,
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:173418:131"/>
                  <hi>It is the Lorde, let him doe what ſeemeth him good; This is my ſorrow and I wil beare it.</hi> Open my eyes withall, that I may ſée thy power, who canſt raiſe the needy from the duſt, and lift the poore out of the doung, and make him fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies like a flocke of ſhéepe, who canſt commaund euen the very rauens to bring bread and fleſh vnto thy ſeruaunts, the Heauens to droppe downe foode, &amp; the rocke of ſtone to yéeld ſtreames of waters, to refreſh thoſe whom thou art pleaſed to prouide for. Shall I thinke thy power to be aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or is thy mercy leſſe then it was wont to be? Haſt thou
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:173418:131"/>
not made a promiſe neuer to forſake me? Am I not alwayes with thée, and doeſt thou not holde mee by my right hand? Shal I imagine thee to be like the bird whom thou haſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of wiſedom, &amp; to whom thou haſt giuen no part of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, who ſheweth himſelfe cruel vnto his young ones, as they were not his, or as if he had trauailed in vain? No, I am aſſured that though a woman ſhould forget her child, &amp; forbeare to haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion on the ſonne of her wombe, yet thou canſt not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get thoſe whom thou loueſt in thy ſonne. Thou knoweſt my wants, thou art able to ſupply
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:173418:132"/>
my wants, thy loue will not ſuffer thee to leaue me deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute in that which thy wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome knowes to bee conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for me. Encreaſe my faith, that I may depend yet more vpon thee, make mee diligent in the place &amp; calling in which thou haſt ſet mee, frame my mind and my deſires to that rate which thou haſt allotted me, kéep mee from vniuſt and vnlawfull courſes, from en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uying the abundance which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers doe enioy: poſſeſſe mee with this perſwaſion, that this my preſent ſtate is the fitteſt for mee, and that when it ſhall be good for mee to haue more, thy hand ſhall inſtantly be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:173418:132"/>
toward me: Stirre me vp to ſeeke thy kingdome, and labour for the meat which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dureth vnto life eternall. En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich my ſoule with ſpirituall bleſſings in heauenly things: perſwade my conſcience of thy loue in Chriſt Ieſus, that the féeling thereof may make all things ſwéete vnto mee. Cauſe me both to truſt and to waite for thy ſaluation, and in all things to ſtriue to giue thee thy deſerued glory, and all this in and for thy Sonnes ſake my onely Mediatour and Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. Amen. <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="prayer">
               <pb n="230" facs="tcp:173418:133"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>31. Another of like</hi> nature, fit for one whom God hath enriched vvith outvvard things.</head>
               <p>IT hath pleaſed thee (O Lord) out of the freedome of thy bountie, to deale more largely with mee then with many of thy ſeruants, and to furniſh me with ſtore of thoſe outward bleſſings, which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers (euery way as good by nature as my ſelfe) doe not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy. My heart is fraughted with much corruption: and though riches be in themſelues a bleſſing, yet without thy e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeciall grace, they will bee
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:173418:133"/>
vnto me an occaſion of many euils. Apt I ſhall be to lift vp my heart, to pride my ſelfe in my own conceipt, to truſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my welth, to deſpiſe others, to grow in loue with this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent world, to become cold and remiſſe in the beſt ſeruices, to conclude that I am highly in thy fauour, becauſe thou haſt enriched me. Theſe be the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, which through the poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of our nature, do riſe by theſe outward hauings, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can I ſay that my heart is cleane from theſe corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Purge them out of mée (I beſeech thee) by the fierie power of thy ſpirit: Giue me pouertie of ſpirit and humble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:173418:134"/>
of minde, amid this out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward fulneſſe with which thou haſt endued me. Make mee to remember that the more I haue, the greater ſhall bee mine account, and the harder for me to be ſaued: that by that meanes, my wealth may be ſo far from puffing mee vp with ſecure preſumtion, that it may moue me y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rather euen w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fear and trembling to work out my ſaluation. Cauſe me to think often vpon the wordes of my Sauiour, that riches are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful, and of a thorny nature, choking the good ſéed of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word and making it to become vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitfull: that ſo I may learne carefully to handle them and
<pb n="233" facs="tcp:173418:134"/>
to vſe them with great héedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and circumſpection, leſt I ſhould by them gal &amp; wound my conſcience, or bee pearced through with many ſorrowes. It is ſaid (O Lord) that theſe high places of the world are ſlipperie places, in which it is hard to go with a right foote, &amp; to kéepe ſtrait and euen ſteps; Oh, ſtir me vp to ſo much the more care to ponder my paths and to take diligent héed vnto my waies; ſuffer me not to iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtify my ſelf to mine own ſoule, or to make my ſelf beléeue that I am as I ought to be, becauſe waters of a full cuppe are wrung vnto mee: but teach me ſeriouſly to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider, that as
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:173418:135"/>
many of thy beloued ſeruants do feele the ſmart of pouerty, ſo euen the moſt wicked and thoſe which do rebelliouſly trangreſſe, haue a large por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in this life, liuing, waxing olde and growing in wealth, their goods oftentimes excée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the very deſires of their hearts. Grant therefore that I may labour for ſome better &amp; more certain aſſura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of thy grace, not grounding my hope vpon my wealth: but reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing in this, if the due conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the daunger and vanitie of abundance may worke by thy bleſſing, to the abaſing and humbling of my heart. Oh let not mine eyes
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:173418:135"/>
be dazled, nor my hart bewit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, with the glory and ſwéet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of theſe worldly trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, which may bée taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me, or I from them euen in the twinkling of an eye: drawe my affections to the loue of that durable riches, and to that fruite of heauenly wiſedome, which is better then gold, and the reuenues whereof do ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe the ſiluer, that my chiefe care may bee to haue a ſoule enriched and furniſhed with thy grace, fulfilled with the knowledge of thy will, in all wiſedome and ſpirituall vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding. And becauſe (O Lord) in hauing much, I am but a ſteward vnder thee,
<pb n="236" facs="tcp:173418:136"/>
and a diſpoſer of thy gifts, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large my bowels towardes o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, make me rich &amp; fruitfull in good workes, being a father to the poore, and cauſing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hart of the widow to reioyce, war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the loynes of the naked with the fleece of my ſhéep, not eating my morſels alone, but dealing my bread to the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie, and neuer hiding my ſelf from mine owne fleſh. For why ſhould I make gold my hope? or wherefore ſhould I ſtriue to lade my ſelfe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this thicke clay, ſtill plotting to ſet my neaſt on high, when al that I haue or can haue is in a moment turned into va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie? Quicken mee vppe
<pb n="237" facs="tcp:173418:136"/>
therefore to good duties, that the hearts of thy Saints may bee comforted by mee, and that in the place where I liue, I may by my forwardneſſe draw on and prouoke others to all the offices of neceſſarie beneuolence. Let the bowels of the néedie bee my treaſurie, and let it bee my deſire &amp; care there to lay vp in ſtore a good foundation for my ſelf againſt the time to come, not truſting to be crowned for the worth of my liberalitie (for what can that be to a <hi>Weight of glory?</hi>) but aſſuring my ſelf y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy ſhewed by me vnto others, is a beam of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loue which ſhines fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee vpon my ſoule. Thus
<pb n="238" facs="tcp:173418:137"/>
(O Lord) ſhall I by thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe haue the true vſe of thy bleſſings, together with a dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly encreaſe of much matter of thankeſgiuing for thy great goodnes to mee ſo vile and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthie; and all for Chriſt, and in his moſt glorious and holie name: to whom with thee and thy ſpirit, one true euerlaſting and only wiſe God, bee all praiſe, and power, might, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie and dominion now and euermore, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="prayer">
               <pb n="239" facs="tcp:173418:137"/>
               <head>32. A Prayer for the whole State.</head>
               <p>EXtraordinarie (O Lord) haue thy fauours beene vnto this Kingdom; when we recount our long co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued peace, our victories, our plentie, our comfort by religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and prudent gouernors: eſpecially, the glorious light of thy Goſpell which hath ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned amongſt vs, our fréedome from the miſerable bondage of Romiſh and Antichriſtian ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannie: wee muſt needes ſay, that thou haſt not dealt ſo with euerie Nation. Indeede the crie of our ſinnes is great,
<pb n="240" facs="tcp:173418:138"/>
the verie heauens may bluſh to looke vpon vs, and the earth is wearie to beare our groſſe, our ſhameles, our preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous euils: Thou thy ſelfe (O patient God, art preſſed vnder vs, as a cart is preſſed that is full of ſheaues: Long haſt thou waited for our repentance, and often haſt thou vrged vs by the Miniſters of thy word, to break off our ſins, and euen beſought vs by them to bee reconciled vnto thee. But wee haue ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be reformed, wee haue caſt thy word behind vs, thou haſt ſtretched out thy hand, and wee would not regarde; wee haue deſpiſed and mocked thy meſſengers, our hearts
<pb n="241" facs="tcp:173418:138"/>
within vs haue beene fully ſet to do euill. Mercie hath beene offered, wee haue not eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med it: iudgement hath beene threatned, wee haue not feared it: the very triall of our counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances teſtifieth againſt vs, wee declare our ſinnes as <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> wee hide them not; all manner of foule enormities do march openly and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently and without feare in our ſtreets. How iuſtly migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt thou powre out euen the vials of thy wrath vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vs to be a deteſtation, and a curſe, and an aſtoniſhment, and a reproch to other Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, forcing vs to wring out and to drinke the very dregs of
<pb n="242" facs="tcp:173418:139"/>
that mixt wine of thy fierce &amp; terrible indignation. If thou ſhouldeſt bring an vtter diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution and deſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon our State, making our enemies to ride ouer ouer our heades, to clime aboue vs vp on hie, and vs to come downe beneath belowe: If thou ſhouldeſt take away from vs the Iudge and the Prophet, the honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and the Counſeller, and appoint children to bee our Princes: If thou ſhouldeſt make heaps of our Cities, and leaue our Townes without inhabitants; If thou ſhouldſt at once quench the light of thy bleſſed word, and giue vs ouer to the ſeruice of dumbe idols,
<pb n="243" facs="tcp:173418:139"/>
and our ſoules to be ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vp in the darkeneſſe of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh ignorance and ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; if thou ſhouldeſt make vs by thy iudgements a prouerb and a ſpectacle to the whole world, it were no other then wée haue deſerued; nay, it is thy great mercie, that theſe things, and more heauie then theſe, haue not already ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken vs. But (O Lord) bee mercifull to our ſinnes for thy names ſake: O thou which art the God of grace, looke graciouſly vpon vs in the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator of grace, Chriſt Ieſus. Wee haue nothing to plead, but his merite, nothing can waſh away the fouleneſſe of
<pb n="244" facs="tcp:173418:140"/>
our ſinnes, but his moſt preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous bloud; Make (wee pray thee) our hearts to mourne within vs, both for our owne perſonall ſinnes, and for al the abominations which are done in the midſt of the Land: Oh that we might turne vnto thee with al our heart, with faſting, with weeping, and with ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing; Oh that we could ſée the thinges that belong vnto our peace: and might euerie man turne from his euill way, and from the wickedneſſe that is in his hand, and make his wayes &amp; his workes good. Let it be thy holy pleaſure (we hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beſeech thée) to continue and to enlarge thy wonted fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours
<pb n="245" facs="tcp:173418:140"/>
towardes vs; Stabliſh this our peaceable gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by a perpetuall and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable decree. Compaſſe-in this Ila<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, with thy fauor, as with a ſhield; Let neuer thine and our aduerſaries, roare in the midſt of thy congregation, or ſette vppe their banners as ſignes of victorie and conqueſt ouer vs. Aboue all (O Lord) vouchſafe the comfort of thy Goſpell, and the libertie of thy bleſſed truth: Grant that that may ſtill be faithfully &amp; ſoundly preached in our Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. Oh remooue not our ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dleſtick, though our falling fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our firſt loue, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> uniuerſall ſlaking of our zeal, hath deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb n="246" facs="tcp:173418:141"/>
it. Lengthen out the vſe of it (we entreat thee) euen ſo long as the Sun and Moone endureth, that by it thoſe that are yet vnborn, and ſhal come out of our Loynes, may bee guided and directed in the way of peace. And to this end, wée are moſt humble and inſtant ſuters to thy Maieſtie, euen to thee by whom Kings raigne, and whoſe dominion and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraintie reacheth ouer all; that thou wouldeſt multiplie thy bleſſings vpon thy King, euen thine annointed (King <hi>Iames</hi>) whoſe head thou haſt lifted vp aboue others, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whoſe hands thou haſt com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mitted the raines of theſe vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="247" facs="tcp:173418:141"/>
Kingdomes. O Lorde, when we remember the dayes by-paſt, euen the dayes of our feare, how that after the death of our late renowned Queen, we looked for nothing but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſuppoſing that the times of our peace muſt needs haue died with her, and haue euen beene buried in her graue, and conſider withall, how thou then, without any ſo much as drawing of a ſword, or colour of commotion, placedſt in her throne a King of the ſame roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all bloud, and of the ſame loue and affection to thy holy truth, vnder whoſe ſhadow, wee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy all the accuſtomed com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of our ancient peace, we
<pb n="248" facs="tcp:173418:142"/>
are like to them that dream, we are euen ſtroke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; ſo far haue all thinges gone beyond our hopes, &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded our exſpectations. O pardon our great vngrateful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that paſſe ouer thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies ſo ſuperficially, and do ſo ſeldome and ſo ſlightly medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate vpon thy kindneſſe. Let not our vnthankefulneſſe turn away thy intended bleſſings from vs; ſtabliſh his throne (we beſéech thée) let his ſoule be bound in the bu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dle of life with thee, &amp; caſt out the ſoule of his enemies, as out of the middle of a ſling. As thou haſt preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him with liberal bleſſings, and ſet a crowne of pure gold
<pb n="249" facs="tcp:173418:142"/>
vpon his head: ſo let his glorie be great in thy ſaluation, and make him glad with the ioy of thy countenance. Go on to giue him thy iudgments, that the righteous may flouriſh in his dayes, and that hee may iudge the poore of the people, and ſaue the children of the née<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, &amp; ſubdue the oppreſſor: Let him not wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t a man of his own line, to ſit vpon his ſeat: but continue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdom in his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteritie, vntil the time in which al earthly kingdomes muſt be determined. And as thou haſt made his Quéen, like a fruitful vine on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſides of his houſe, &amp; a ioyful mother of many royall pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts: ſo we pray thée lay vpon
<pb n="250" facs="tcp:173418:143"/>
her much dignitie and honor; &amp; bleſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both out of <hi>Zion,</hi> ſo that they may ſee the wealth of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> all their dayes. Let their children bee as choſen ſhafts in thy quiuer, make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as the plants growing vp in their youth, and as the corner ſtones grauen after the ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of a palace. Chiefely we beſeech thee to poure out a large meaſure of thy bleſſings vpon the young Prince <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie:</hi> enrich him with all prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vertues; water him ſo with thy heauenly dew, that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of thy truth, zeale for thy glorie, loue to thy Church, perfite hatred of Popiſh Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie, may in him growe vp
<pb n="251" facs="tcp:173418:143"/>
with his years, that ſo he may alſo in his appointed time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come another Inſtrument vnder thee, for the further en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>largement of thy Goſpel, and the proſperitie and happineſſe of theſe Realmes. Alwayes afford thy gratious preſence to thoſe honorable Lords of his Maieſties Councill: be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thou the Preſident at their Table, direct their conſultati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſanctifie their policies, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their purpoſes, and guide all their courſes to ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions as may bee moſt for thy glorie, the honour of the King, the peace of the State, and the comfort of thy choſen. Bleſſe all the Iudges, Sages
<pb n="252" facs="tcp:173418:144"/>
and Magiſtrates of the State, make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as hiding places fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wind, &amp; as a refuge for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> oppreſſed; cauſe them euer to remember that they are thy Miniſters for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peoples wealth, &amp; that they execute not the iudgements of man but of the Lord; &amp; that although thou haſt honored them with thine own name, calling them gods, yet they ſhal die as men, &amp; fall like others: that ſo iudgement may not be turned into gal, nor the fruite of righteouſnes into wormewood, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iuſtice may be executed truly &amp; vprightly in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gates, &amp; al things may be to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> praiſe of them that do wel &amp; to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> puniſhment of thoſe that are
<pb n="253" facs="tcp:173418:144"/>
workers of iniquitie. Neither may we (O Lord) forget thoſe who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt put in the ſeruice of thy church, to féed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> flock which dependeth on them, to rule the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; to go in &amp; out before them, &amp; to labour in the worde and in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. Thou (O Chriſt) art the chief ſhepheard &amp; biſhop of our ſoules, thou art the Lorde of the harueſt, build vp (wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſéech thée) the breaches of thy Church, make the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes thereof to breake foorth (yet more) as the light, &amp; the ſaluation thereof as a burning lampe. Continue the ſtanding and encreaſe the number of thoſe ſeeing watchmen, whom thou haſt placed vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> walls
<pb n="254" facs="tcp:173418:145"/>
of <hi>Ieruſalem;</hi> ſtirre them vp that they ceaſe not, day nor nor night, working the worke with which thou haſt entru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted them, and faithfully diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſing that word of reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation which thou haſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to them. Kindle in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the zeale of <hi>Samuel,</hi> that they may ſay, <hi>God forbid that we ſhould ſin againſt the Lorde, &amp; ceaſe praying for the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and ſhewing them the good &amp; the right way:</hi> Make them with <hi>Paul</hi> to ſay, <hi>Woe vnto vs if wee preach not the Goſpell.</hi> And be pleaſed alſo ſo to bleſſe their endeuours, &amp; to proſper their labours, by giuing them a doore of vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,
<pb n="255" facs="tcp:173418:145"/>
and by preſeruing them from vnreaſonable and euill men, that they may from eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry part of the Land bring ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſheaues into thy barne, and that dayly thoſe that are ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto life eternall may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue. And for a continuall ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply and nurſerie to thy Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches amongſt vs, bleſſe the Vniuerſities and Schooles of learning; let not thoſe foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines (O Lord) bee poyſoned with any popiſh leauen: but grant that the doctrine which is according to godlineſſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taught &amp; profeſſed in them in ſinceritie, by the yong pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts there ſpringing vp, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> decais of congregations abroad may be
<pb n="256" facs="tcp:173418:146"/>
renued, and euerie place may be furniſhed with a Paſtor af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thy owne heart, which may féed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people with knowledge and with vnderſtanding. And (Lorde) reſtraine and reforme the gréedineſſe of thoſe which muzzle their mouthes which ſhould tread out the corne, and bring foorth the foode of life vnto thy people, which reſpect not the <hi>Leuite,</hi> but abridge the hire of the labourer, and ſay one to another, <hi>Let vs take to our po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the habitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of God.</hi> Throughout the Land and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all the inhabitants ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, plant the true knowledge &amp; feare of thee, loyalty to their ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraine, obedience to all ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate
<pb n="257" facs="tcp:173418:146"/>
authoritie, loue &amp; reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to their ſpiritual guides vnitie of affection, mercie and compaſſion either to other. And inaſmuch as (O Lorde) wee haue continuall experience of the malice of the diuell, in ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſéedes of ſedition and treaſon in mens hearts, and in rayſing vp the ſonnes of <hi>Behal</hi> to ouercaſt (if it might be) the faire day of our peace, with a cloud of helliſh co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; we pray thée, without whom no enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſes canne bee eſtabliſhed, to make voyd their hopes, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer their practiſes, and (as thou haſt hitherto euen mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culouſly done) to turne their deuiſes vpon their owne heads
<pb n="258" facs="tcp:173418:147"/>
for their own confuſion. There come dayly out of that Pit of <hi>Rome,</hi> many Locuſts: and fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that Sea, there is ſent among vs a continual ſpawne of new conſpirators: theſe encourage themſelues in wicked purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, they commune together to lay ſnares, miſchiefe they ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine againſt the quiet of the Land; It vexeth them to ſée the thriuing of the Goſpell, and the grouth of thy truth, and they do euen breath out threatnings and ſlaughters againſt the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors thereof. Let not (O Lord) their imaginations proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, let their eyes fall out with looking for that day which they haue long deſired; Let thy
<pb n="259" facs="tcp:173418:147"/>
hand, euen thy right hand, find the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out: &amp; if they belong not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thée, make them like a fierie ouen in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of thine anger, deſtroy their fruit from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth and their ſéed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the children of men, put them apart, and make ready y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtrings of thy bowe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their faces. And as for vs (O Lord) ſuffer vs not to were wanton with the bleſſings of peace, nor to forget to render to thée according to thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes beſtowed: but grant that thy kindneſſes may bind vs more ſtrongly vnto thee, &amp; that wee may reſolue by thy grace to ſerue thee faithfully, who w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vs dealſt ſo graciouſly, &amp; that in &amp; for Chriſt Ieſus ſake thy ſon &amp; our Sauiour, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:173418:148"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:173418:148"/>
            <head>A Table of the Prayers <hi>contained in this Booke.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>A Morning prayer for pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate families. pag. 1.</item>
               <item>An Euening praier for priuate families. p. 15</item>
               <item>A Morning prayer for a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate perſon. p. 35</item>
               <item>An Euening prayer for a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate perſon. p. 44</item>
               <item>A more particular Morning prayer for the ſabaoth day. p. 55</item>
               <item>A prayer before the hearing of the word. p. 64</item>
               <item>A praier before the receiuing the Sacrament of the Lords Supper. p. 72</item>
               <item>A thankeſgiuing after. p. 78</item>
               <item>A prayer for the afflicted in what kind ſoeuer. p. 80</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:173418:149"/>A prayer in reſpect of ſome loſſe, as of Honor, Goods. &amp;c. p. 88</item>
               <item>A prayer fitted to the loſſe of an eſpeciall friend, as Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Husband, &amp;c. p. 95</item>
               <item>A prayer applyed to the ſtate of a man inwardly perplex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the horror of ſinne, with doubtings of Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, and with the tentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ſatan tending to deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire. p. 100</item>
               <item>A prayer then needfull when a man hath ſome ſpeciall combate with ſome one or moe ſpeciall ſins, againſt which he deſireth victorie. p. 115</item>
               <item>A prayer of humiliation and
<pb facs="tcp:173418:149"/>
ſorrow after ſome ſpeciall ſinne committed. p. 120</item>
               <item>A prayer in reſpect of death, needfull at all times, but eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially in ſickeneſſe. p. 131</item>
               <item>A prayer more ſpecially fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the ſtate and occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of a ſicke man. p. 141</item>
               <item>A direction for thoſe who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie to perform the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an dutie of praier for their ſake whome they come to viſite. p. 152</item>
               <item>A thankſgiuing for a ſick man after recouerie. p. 157</item>
               <item>A prayer for a woman in her trauaile. p. 161</item>
               <item>A tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kſgiuing after deliuerie. p. 164</item>
               <item>A prayer for thoſe which are
<pb facs="tcp:173418:150"/>
employed in the aſſiſtance of a trauailing woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. p. 168</item>
               <item>A thankeſgiuing, when God hath bleſſed their paines in the womans deliuerie. p. 170</item>
               <item>A prayer for a ſouldier fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for his Countrey, or the confederates thereof. p. 173</item>
               <item>A prayer for a man trauailing by Sea about his lawful bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe. p. 178</item>
               <item>A Prayer applyed to the ſtate of a Malefactor, condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by law to die, &amp; draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the time of executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. p. 184</item>
               <item>A prayer riſing out of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious meditation of the laſt Iudgement. p. 193</item>
               <item>A prayer fitted to the time
<pb facs="tcp:173418:150"/>
of warre. p. 202</item>
               <item>Another of like nature, reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the time of Dearth and Famine. p. 207</item>
               <item>Another like, applyed to the time of ſome great contagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. p. 215</item>
               <item>A meditation or prayer for a poore man. p. 220</item>
               <item>Another of like nature, for one whom God hath enriched with outward things p. 230</item>
               <item>A prayer for the whole State. 239</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:173418:151" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:173418:151" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
